<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ProjectStates>
  <StateTransition stage="eProjFacTypeVernacular" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator" RequiresUsingVernacular="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator enters in story language</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
By this stage, you will have already crafted and recorded a story according to the procedure you 
learned in the workshop.

Now have the Project Facilitator listen line-by-line to the recording and type it in the story 
line box shown in this window.

You can type the entire story into a single line box. Then when you're finished, click on the 
"Story" menu, "Re-align story verses" option to have the story split into sentences so that each 
line has a single sentence in it.

The lines will be split into sentences based on Sentence Final punctuation (i.e. ".!?", etc). If 
your language has special sentence final punctuation (e.g. the Hindi Danda '।' or the Arabic '؟'), 
you will want to add these to the list of sentence final punctuation in the 'Project' menu, 
'Settings' command, on the appropriate 'Language' tab. When entering special punctuation, be sure 
to enter the plain (most common) 'full stop' punctuation character as the first one and use no 
spaces between the characters. This (first) character will be used for any sentences that don't 
have a full stop (i.e. if you forget one, then it will be added to the sentence).

When you are finished, click on the "Select State" menu item to bring up the list of states for
this story. To move forward (which is the only possible direction in this state), click the (green) 
state button. 

If this is a story from the Bible, then a dialog window will be displayed asking you to type in 
the purpose that this story is in the set; that is, why have you chosen this particular story? 
How does it fit with the theme of your panorama? You will also enter the list of resources used 
in crafting the story (audio recordings of Bibles, videos, etc).
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacTypeNationalBT</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacTypeInternationalBT</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacAddAnchors</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckNonBiblicalStory</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="false" viewEnglishBTField="false" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestions="false" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eProjFacTypeNationalBT" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator" RequiresUsingNationalBT="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator enters National language BT</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the project facilitator) will enter the "back-translation" of the story 
into the national language (e.g. Hindi) that you recorded from the UNS.

Be sure to type the UNS's back-translation into the same line number as the story verse to the 
left, so that the back-translation matches what's in the story verse.

You can repeatedly click the "Story" menu, "Re-align story verses" item (or press Ctrl+F5) to 
re-adjust all lines until they match up. If you use a sentence final punctuation in the story
line, then you need to use the same punctuation in the National BT line as well, so they will
be split into lines accurately. This will insure that you have the proper punctuation in both 
the story lines and in the National language back-translation lines.

When you are finished entering the national language back-translation, then click the 
"Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the next (green) state button. 
When you do, another window will be displayed in which you will be asked to identify the UNS 
that did the back-translation. You can also access this and other story information by clicking, 
"Story", and then "Story Information" item.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacTypeInternationalBT</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacAddAnchors</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckNonBiblicalStory</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacTypeVernacular</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="false" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestions="false" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eProjFacTypeInternationalBT" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator" RequiresUsingEnglishBT="true" RequiresUsingOtherEnglishBTer="false">
    <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator enters English BT</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the project facilitator) will enter the English back-translation (BT) of the story.
If you are also using the national language for a back-translation field (which was from a UNS), then 
you can do the English BT yourself. However, it should be based on the national language BT rather than 
the story language. If this project doesn't use a national language BT, then the English BT should be 
done by a UNS directly and you (the project facilitator) will just type in their back-translation.

If none of the UNSs or anyone on the crafting team understands English well enough to do an English 
back-translation, you may be able to arrange with your consultant to have someone else who knows 
both the national language and English do the English back-translation for you. To do this, you must 
add that person to your team with the "Outside English back-translator" role (see "Project", 
"Settings", and then check that box on the "Team Members" tab). 

If you have an outside English back-translator member, then instead of this state, the program will 
go to the stage where the English back-translation is entered after you have entered the anchors and 
testing questions (because the testing questions will need to be translated into English as well).

But first, discuss with your consultant whether an English back-translation is even needed and whether 
it can be done by someone else. As long as the first back-translation is done by a UNS, then it's okay 
to add an 'Outside English back-translator' team member to do the English back-translation. 

When you are finished entering the English back-translation, then click the "Select State" menu item 
and in the resulting window click on the next (green) state. 
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacAddAnchors</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckNonBiblicalStory</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacTypeVernacular</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacTypeNationalBT</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestions="false" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eProjFacAddAnchors" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator adds Anchors</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the project facilitator) will go through the story verse-by-verse and look up one or more Bible references in the Bible pane 
that supports the information in the verse. These Bible references are known as "Anchors", because they tie the story verse to the Bible.

When you find a supporting Bible passage in the "Bible" pane (lower-left pane of the OneStory editor), then click and hold down the left mouse 
button on the button to the left of the verse text. Then while the left mouse button is held down, drag the mouse onto the line in the story 
verse area above with the label, "anc:". This is the anchor bar for the verse. When the mouse is over the anchor bar, release the left mouse 
button and a new "anchor button" will appear on the anchor bar for that passage.

Once anchor buttons are in the anchor bar, you can click on them to jump to the referenced verse. You can also right-click on the anchor button 
for other options, like adding a comment to the anchor (e.g. "implied by ..."). These comments will be displayed when you hover the mouse over 
an anchor button (and in historical difference and print preview versions of the story). You can also add a cultural or exegetical note about 
the anchor by right-clicking on the anchor button and choosing "Add Exegetical/Cultural Note". Such notes can help the consultant understand 
why you chose the Bible reference that you did.

In this stage, you can also select the key terms that are in the story line. To do this, right-click on the Anchor bar and choose "Edit Key 
Terms". This will bring up the Key Terms dialog box which will show you all the Key biblical terms associated with your anchored bible 
references. It will also list all the story verses in your project which use the same key term as those in the anchored scripture passages. 
This is so that you can make sure that you are using the same term in each place where the same underlying Greek or Hebrew key term is used.

When you are finished adding one or more anchors for each verse, then click the 'Next Stage' button in the left-hand side of the status bar 
to go to the next stage in the process.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacAddStoryQuestions</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacTypeVernacular</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacTypeNationalBT</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacTypeInternationalBT</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="false" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eProjFacAddStoryQuestions" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator adds story testing questions</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the project facilitator) will go through the story and add "Story Testing Questions" (STQs). These are questions that you will eventually ask an 
uninitiated native speaker (UNS) in order to test the implications of the story.

The best kind of STQs are those that invite the UNS to speculate on "Why" or "How" of what is going on in the story. Or questions that ask, "What kinds of 
things might be an example of this?" are also useful. They should be based on the story, but you should try to get the UNS to speculate beyond what the story 
itself says. For example, suppose that the story had a verse like, "And the people took baptism and left their sins". You could ask a question like, "Why (or 
how) do you think they took baptism?" or "How (or why) do you think they left their sins?" These would be good questions, because the answer isn't in the story 
and based on what the UNS thinks, it might be necessary to change the story to avoid a wrong understanding. 

Other kinds of questions that begin with "What", "Who", "When", "Where", are usually not as good, especially if they can be answered from the story itself. For 
example, suppose the story verse says, "Jesus and three of his disciples went up on a hill..." Then the question, "How many disciples went up on the hill with 
Jesus?" would not be a good question, because the answer was just mentioned in the story. Such questions are known as "closed questions" and are not good 
questions to test the story. However, such questions can be useful if the story itself is ambiguous. For example, if the story line were, "He said to Eve...", 
since there are two possible referents of 'He' (the snake and Adam), you could ask "Who do you think said this to Eve?" to make sure that the UNS understood 
the correct reference.

Also, story testing questions shouldn’t be questions for which the answer is either "yes" or "no". For example, a question like, "Did Joseph reveal himself to 
his brothers before they left?" Also, questions about what something means are not good questions. For example, "What does the phrase "sabt din" mean?". 
These are examples of questions that are not good story testing questions.

Also, they also shouldn’t be questions which ask the UNS for their personal beliefs or theological opinion (e.g. "Do you think that God could really have 
created the world in 6 days?") or questions which can't really help the story regardless of the answer (e.g. "In your opinion can a person stay in a cattle 
shed?"). Besides being a "yes-no" question, this one can't possibly help correct any misinterpretation from the story, regardless of what answer is given.

When you think of questions to ask, keep in mind what kind of answer you might get from the UNS. If the answer could show that they misunderstood the 
situation in the story, then it's probably a good question.

Depending on what agreement you make with your consultant and coach, you may need to translate the testing questions you create into English so the 
consultant and coach can review them. However, remember that these questions should always be asked and answered with the UNS in the story language itself; 
not the national language, nor in English. And they should use the exact same wording as in the story itself. So, for example, if the story said, "Adam was 
given the fruit and he ate.", then don't word the question as, "Why do you think Eve gave the fruit to Adam to eat?" (since the story verse didn't mention 
Eve, you shouldn't add her to the question).

You should have at least half as many story testing questions as verses in the story. So if your story is 20 verses long, then you need to have at least 10 
questions, and don't forget that it's okay if some verses have multiple questions. If you have trouble coming up with enough questions, then contact your 
consultant for some suggestions.

When you are finished adding these testing questions, then click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the next (green) state. 
At that time, you will be asked whether you want to enter the results (retelling and answers to the testing questions) from a UNS test (click 'Yes') or 
whether you want to the story and questions as they are passed by the consultant first for pre-UNS test checking (click 'No'). Discuss with your consultant 
which one you should choose.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition AllowToSkip="true">eConsultantCheckStoryInfo</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReadyForTest1</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacTypeVernacular</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacTypeNationalBT</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacTypeInternationalBT</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacAddAnchors</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eProjFacRevisesBeforeUnsTest" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator" DontShowTilPast="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator revises the story (before UNS test)</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the project facilitator) will go through the feedback given by the consultant in the Consultant 
Notes pane and revise your story before doing a UNS test. Generally, you will be in this state when the consultant
wants you to make some change to the story and they want to review your changes before having you go on to do a UNS 
test. So they will have moved the story *backwards* from a later state into this earlier state for you to make changes.

As you process the consultant's comments, decide on the appropriate change for each comment and then get the crafter
to make a new recording incorporating all of the changes.

Once you and the crafter have made revisions/corrections and have a new recording, then update the story line text 
boxes with the change as well as the national language and English back-translations. 

For each comment by the consultant (in the 'cons:' field of the 'Consultant Notes' pane) you should type in some 
response in the boxes labeled 'prfc:' (for Project Facilitator) to close the loop on the conversation (even just "done" 
is fine). If you have further questions, it's okay to ask for clarification in another line. You can add another line 
for additional comments by right-clicking on the small button and choosing "Add Note" if one is not already visible.

When you are finished, then click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the next (green) 
state.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckStoryInfo</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eBackTranslatorTypeInternationalBT" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eEnglishBacktranslator" RequiresUsingEnglishBT="true" RequiresUsingOtherEnglishBTer="true">
    <StageDisplayString>English back-translator enters the English back-translation</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, someone typically outside of the crafting team will translate the National language 
back translation of the story into English (or from the story language if not using the national 
language back-translation). This is useful for when the crafting team doesn't know English well and 
someone else can do the back-translation from the national language (which was done by a UNS) into 
English. 

This stage only occurs if you have an "Outside English Back-translator" member on your team and it 
occurs after all the Project Facilitator states are finished and just before the story goes to the 
consultant. During this stage, you, the outside English back-translator will translate the story 
from the National back-translation as well as the story testing questions into English.

When you are finished entering the English back translation, then click the "Select State" menu item 
and in the resulting window click on the next (green) state.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckNonBiblicalStory</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckStoryInfo</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotesBeforeUnsTest" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eEnglishBacktranslator" RequiresUsingEnglishBT="true" RequiresUsingOtherEnglishBTer="true" DontShowTilPast="true">
    <StageDisplayString>English back-translator translates Consult. Notes for PF (before UNS test)</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the English back-translator) will go through the feedback given by the consultant in
the Consultant Notes pane and translate it into the national language for the project facilitator.

You can just type the translation into the same box as the original consultant note, though you'll have
to manually turn on the proper keyboard as needed.

This state is used when the consultant is returning the story to the team for revision *before* going
on to the UNS test. So when you are finished translating the feedback for the Project Facilitator, then 
click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the previous (red) state 'Project 
Facilitator revises the story before returning it to the Consultant'. Then close the editor and the file 
will be uploaded to the internet where it can be downloaded by the project facilitator for changes.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckNonBiblicalStory</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckStoryInfo</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eConsultantCheckNonBiblicalStory" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining" RequiresNonBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Consultant checks the discourse features of the story</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) will help the team chart this story in the "Discourse Chart 
Helper" program.

To copy the story from this program to use in the Discourse Chart Helper program, you can click 
'Edit', 'Copy', 'Story' command and then paste the copied text into the 'Workspace' area at the 
bottom of that Discourse Chart Helper program.

See the instructions in the 'Start', 'All Programs', 'SIL Converters', 'Help', 'Readme for 
Discourse Chart Helper' program for details.

This is the final stage of the process for this non-biblical story.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestions="false" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eFirstPassMentorCheck1" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eFirstPassMentor" RequiresFirstPassMentor="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>First-pass mentor checks the story (pre-UNS test)</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the first-pass mentor) will check the story and make any suggestions you can think of that would make the story more 
accurate, clear, and natural. You will put your suggestions in the 'Consultant Notes' pane of the editor in the boxes labeled 'cons:'

You can make comments related to any of the following issues:

Anchors: are the lines of the story supported by the anchored verses, or has the story crafter mis-interpreted something?

Story Flow: does the story flow nicely?

Story Length: is the length of the story nice? Does it seem re-tellable?

Translation issues: are any words translated in a way that makes you think it might be mis-translated?

Story matches the stated purpose: does the story seem to support the purpose for which it was created? (see 'Story' menu, 'Story 
    Information' to see the 'Purpose'). The redemptive theme is also supposed to be written up in the first tab of the 'Show Panorama' 
    command.
    
Were enough resources used: look in 'Story' menu, 'Story Information' again to see the list of resources used in crafting the story. 
    Where possible, there should be at least two Bible versions and two visual resources (video and pictures) used when crafting a story.

Story Testing Questions: are the story testing questions appropriate for the kind of testing that we want in a Storying project? e.g. do 
    they cause the UNS to think outside of the text--"why" and "how" questions are better than "what", "who", "where", "when" kind of 
    questions)? Have the they avoided questions whose answers are "yes" and "no" or questions which ask what something means? Is there a 
    answer to the question which would be beneficial for checking the inferences of the story?

If there are major problems with the flow and/or thematic focus (e.g. it's too long, or doesn't really support the purpose mentioned), 
you can add a few consultant notes in the Consultant Notes pane and send it back to the Project Facilitator for revision (i.e. before 
spending a lot of time checking it further and/or passing it along to the Consultant). To send it back to the Project Facilitator for 
such changes, click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the previous (red) state 'Project Facilitator 
revises the story before returning it to the Consultant'. Then close the editor (or reload the project file -- i.e. "Project", 
"Recent Projects", "{project name}") and the project file will be uploaded to the internet where it can be downloaded by the project 
facilitator to work on changes.

Otherwise, when you are finished reviewing the Story and adding consultant notes in the 'Consultant Notes' pane, then click the "Select 
State" menu item and choose the next (green) state.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckStoryInfo</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eConsultantCheckStoryInfo" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Consultant checks the story information (pre-UNS test)</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) will check to make sure that the Project Facilitator has 
entered the following information properly (click the 'Story' menu, 'Story Information' command):

    the crafter's name
    the purpose for this story (does it fit within their redeptive theme--See 'Show Panorama' command)
    the resources used (are the multiple and oral?)
    the name and details about the UNS that did the back-translation
    
You can also take a first pass read through the story to make sure that it flows nicely and fits
within the purpose for which it was created. 

If there are major problems with the flow and/or thematic focus (e.g. it's too long, or doesn't 
really support the purpose mentioned), you can add a few consultant notes in the 'cons:' fields 
in the 'Consultant Notes' pane and send it back to the Project Facilitator for revision (i.e. 
before spending a lot of time checking it further). To send it back to the Project Facilitator 
for such revisions, click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the 
previous (red) state 'Project Facilitator revises the story before returning it to the 
Consultant'. Then close the editor (or reload the project file -- i.e. "Project", "Recent Projects", 
"{project name}") and the project file will be uploaded to the internet where it can be downloaded 
by the project facilitator to work on changes.

Otherwise, when you are finished reviewing the Story Information, then click the "Select State" 
menu item and and choose the next (green) state.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition AllowToSkip="true">eConsultantCheckAnchors</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition AllowToSkip="true">eConsultantCheckStoryQuestions</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eCoachReviewRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestions="false" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eConsultantCheckAnchors" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Consultant checks the story anchors (pre-UNS test)</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) will check the anchors added by the project facilitator for each line of the 
story.

The anchors shown in the Story pane are actually buttons. If you click on one, it will jump to the referenced 
passage in the Bible pane. You need to make sure that all the information in each story line is covered by the 
anchored verse(s). If the story line has information which is not in the anchored passages, it's okay for you 
to add further anchors if you can think of a scripture passage which supports what the story crafter is trying 
say (or add a consultant note for the project facilitator to look up the passage and add the anchor themselves).

As you evaluate whether the story verse is a valid interpretation of the anchored verses, in addition to the 
text in the Bible pane, it is recommended that you look in Translator's Workplace exegetical resources. If you 
find a passage in a good exegetical resource that supports the rendering of the story crafter (when, perhaps, 
the scripture passage in the Bible pane doesn't seem to support it), then you can copy the reference from TW 
and paste it into an exegetical comment line (right-click on an anchor button in the Story pane and choose 
"Add cultural/exegetical note" and paste the comment from TW).

As you look up passages in the Bible pane, you can right-click on the book name combo box to move to other books 
in the Bible or click the up/down arrows to shift to the next/previous verse, chapter or book.

Just as you can "drag/drop" the anchor buttons from the Bible pane to the Anchor bar in the Story pane of the 
editor, you can also drag/drop anchor buttons to a red-outlined (editable) box in the Consultant Notes pane as 
well. This will copy the Bible reference into your consultant note and then when the project facilitator sees 
that reference in the Consultant Note, it will be displayed as a hyperlink so that they can just click on it to 
jump to it from the Consultant Notes pane as well.

When you are finished checking all the anchors, then click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting 
window click on the next (green) state.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition AllowToSkip="true">eConsultantCheckStoryQuestions</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eCoachReviewRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckStoryInfo</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="false" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eConsultantCheckStoryQuestions" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Consultant checks the story testing questions (pre-UNS test)</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) need to check the story testing questions added by the project facilitator.

As you consider the story testing questions (STQs), keep in mind that their function is to test the implications of the story. The best kind of STQ are those 
that invite the UNS to speculate on "Why" or "How" of what is going on in the story. Or questions that ask, "What kinds of things might be an example of this?" 
are also useful. They should be based on the story, but you should try to get the UNS to speculate beyond what the story itself says. For example, suppose that 
the story had a verse like, "And the people took baptism and left their sins". A good question would be, "Why (or how) do you think they took baptism?" or 
"How (or why) do you think they left their sins?" These would be good questions, because the answer isn't in the story and based on what answer the UNS gives, 
it might indicate that the story is giving a wrong understanding.

Less useful are content-questions that begin with "What", "Who", "When", "Where", which can usually be answered from the story itself (e.g. if the story line 
was, "Jesus and three of his disciples went up on a hill..." Then it wouldn't be as useful to ask questions like, "How many disciples went up on the hill with 
Jesus?" or "Where did Jesus go?" Such questions are known as "closed questions", because the answer is in the story itself, and they do not make good questions 
for testing the story. However, such questions can be useful if the story itself is ambiguous. For example, if the story line were, "He said to Eve...", since 
there are two possible referents of 'He' (the snake and Adam), you could ask "Who do you think said this to Eve?" to make sure that the UNS understood the 
correct reference.

Also, story testing questions shouldn’t be "yes-no" questions (questions for which the answer is either "yes" or "no"). For example, a question like, "Did 
Joseph reveal himself to his brothers before they left?" Also, questions about what something means are not good questions. For example, "What does the phrase 
"sabt din" mean?". These are examples of questions that are not good story testing questions.

Also, they also shouldn’t be questions which ask the UNS for their personal beliefs or theological opinion (e.g. "Do you think that God could really have 
created the world in 6 days?"). While they might have an interesting answer to such a question and it may help you learn about their culture better, any answer 
they give to such a question won't help test the implications of the story.

Finally, as you evaluate a question always be thinking about what kind of answer a UNS might give. If the answer can't really help the story regardless of what 
the answer is, then it is not a good question. For example, a question like, "In your opinion can a person stay in a cattle shed?". Besides being a "yes-no" 
question, this one can't possibly help correct any misinterpretation from the story, regardless of what answer the UNS gives.

If you feel that any particular question is not a good question, then add a note to the Consultant Note pane for that line recommending that the project 
facilitator make a change to the question. It is important to indicate why the question is not a good one so that they can learn what our goal is in asking 
the questions. And also, be sure to offer an alternative suggestion.

When you are finished adding these testing questions, then click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the next (green) state. If 
this project is configured for 'Consultant-in-Training with Coaching' (see "Project", "Settings" and on the "Team Members" tab), then the next state will be 
for your Coach to evaluate your feedback and possibly put comments in the Coach Notes pane. If you have a question about your feedback prior to passing your 
comments on to the coach, you can add a question to the Coach Notes pane directly (click "View" menu, "Coach notes field" command to display the Coach Notes 
pane if it isn't visible). Then click the "Add Note" button to add a note (at the relevant line).
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eCoachReviewRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckAnchors</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckStoryInfo</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eConsultantCauseRevisionBeforeUnsTest" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining" RequiresBiblicalStory="true" RequiresManageWithCoaching="true" DontShowTilPast="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Consultant revises feedback based on Coach feedback (going backwards prior to UNS testing)</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) will go through the feedback given by the coach in the Coach Notes
pane and, if necessary, modify or add to your feedback to the project facilitator.

For each comment by the coach (the comments in the "coch:" lines in the Coach Notes pane), you should
give some response to close the loop on the conversation (even just "done" is fine). If you have further
questions, it's okay to ask for clarification in another line.

You can add another line for additional questions/comments by clicking the "Add Note" button if needed.

If you are in this state, it is likely because the Coach was not satisfied with something about the story, 
which will require the Project Facilitator and Crafter to correct the story (before going on to do a UNS 
test). So if you worked with the Project Facilitator directly making the requested changes, then you can 
click 'Next State' to return it to the Coach for review. Otherwise, when you are finished updating your 
feedback, click the 'Select State' button and you will want to go back to a previous (red) state (e.g. 
'Project Facilitator revises the story (before UNS test)') for the Project Facilitator/Crafter to correct 
the story.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eCoachReviewRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="true" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eCoachReviewRound1Notes" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eCoach" RequiresBiblicalStory="true" RequiresManageWithCoaching="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Coach reviews story/CIT feedback (pre-UNS testing)</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the coach) will check the story and the consultant notes added by the 
consultant-in-training (and possibly the first-pass mentor) in the Consultant Notes pane. 
Any feedback you have can be put into a note in the "Coach Notes" pane. Click on the "Add 
Note" button to create a box for entering a comment, which will be labeled, "coch:"

If you are satisfied that the story is ready for a UNS test (after your feedback is 
processed), then click the 'Select State' button and choose the forward (green) state 
button for the 'Consultant revises pre-UNS test notes based on Coach's feedback' state. 
This will put the story into the CIT's state to process your feedback before sending it on 
to the Project Facilitator to make final revisions before the UNS test.

If you would like the story or testing questions revised AND you want to see the new version 
of the story before allowing it to go on for a UNS test, then click the 'Select State' button 
and choose the previous (red) state button for the 'Consultant revises feedback based on Coach 
feedback (going backwards prior to UNS testing)' state. This will send the story back to the 
CIT who will update his/her comments before sending it backwards to the team for revisions/
corrections. Eventually then, you will see the story again before the UNS test is done.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantReviseRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCauseRevisionBeforeUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="false" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="true" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eConsultantReviseRound1Notes" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining" RequiresBiblicalStory="true" RequiresManageWithCoaching="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Consultant revises notes based on Coach's feedback</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) will go through the feedback given by the coach in the Coach Notes
pane and, if necessary, modify or add to your feedback to the crafting team.

For each comment by the coach (the comments in the "coch:" lines in the Coach Notes pane), you should
give some response to close the loop on the conversation (even just "done" is fine). If you have further
questions, it's okay to ask for clarification in another line.

You can add another line for additional comments by clicking on the "Add Note" button if needed.

When you are finished, then click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the 
next (green) state.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eCoachReviewRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="true" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotes" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eEnglishBacktranslator" RequiresUsingEnglishBT="true" RequiresUsingOtherEnglishBTer="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>English back-translator translates Consultant Notes for Project Facilitator</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the English back-translator) will go through the feedback given by the consultant in 
the Consultant Notes pane and translate it into the national language for the project facilitator/crafting
team. 

You can just type the translation into the same box as the original consultant note, though you'll have
to manually turn on the proper keyboard as needed.

When you are finished, then click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the 
next (green) state.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantReviseRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckStoryQuestions</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator revises story based on Consultant's feedback</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the project facilitator) will go through the feedback given by the consultant in the Consultant Notes pane and revise your 
story accordingly. 

As you process the consultant's comments, decide on the appropriate change for each comment and if it's a small change, you can record just that 
changed part and splice the new recording over the old one in the original story recording. It's okay that this will create an odd sounding 
recording with portions from different recording sessions. 

For example, suppose that the back-translation of your story says that some character in the Bible story said something which they didn't really 
say--something which is not anchorable. And the consultant points out that the person really said something else instead. Then you would make a 
recording of the something else (corrected) version and overwrite the quote from the original recording.

If you make your revisions/corrections in this manner (i.e. splicing the revisions in the old recording), then you can also update the story line 
text boxes with the change as well as the national language and English back-translations. But remember, the *change* is to the story *recording*; 
not the back-translations. The documentation of the story and its back-translations are just reflections of the change to the story recording.

For more significant changes, discuss each of them with the crafter and get them to retell the whole story with the requested changes. The crafter 
should avoid looking at the documentation while you discuss the changes with them, so it doesn't prejudice them towards a particular way of saying 
it. Your job as project facilitator is to make sure the requested changes make it into the crafter's new version of the story. If they leave out 
one of the requested changes, then have them retell it again (or splice in the missing piece). This might take several iterations to get all of the 
requested changes.

In addition to updating the story documentation for the new version, you should also type in some response to each of the comments by the consultant 
(i.e. the 'cons:' fields from the 'Consultant Notes' pane). Your responses will go in the boxes labeled 'prfc:' (for Project Facilitator) to close 
the loop on the conversation (even just "done" is fine). If you have further questions, it's okay to ask for clarification in another line. You can 
add another line for additional comments by clicking the "Add Note" button if needed.

When you are finished, then click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the next (green) state.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition AllowToSkip="true">eProjFacOnlineReview1WithConsultant</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition AllowToSkip="true">eProjFacReadyForTest1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTypeInternationalBTTest1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck2</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheck2</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantReviseRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckStoryQuestions</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eProjFacOnlineReview1WithConsultant" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator has optional online review with consultant</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the Project Facilitator) can arrange a time to get online at the same time as the 
consultant so that you can discuss the feedback he or she gave. If your team has a First Pass Mentor, 
that person should also be involved in this discussion so they can learn as well. Finally, if the team
and the consultant don't share a common language, it might also be necessary to have the person who 
does the English Back-translation be present on-line as well to translate between the team and the 
consultant.

Once all of the issues and their resolutions are discussed, then click the "Select State" menu item 
and in the resulting window click on the next (green) state where you will do a UNS test. 
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition AllowToSkip="true">eProjFacReadyForTest1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTypeInternationalBTTest1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck2</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheck2</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantReviseRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheckStoryQuestions</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eProjFacReadyForTest1" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator is ready for a UNS test</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the Project Facilitator) will do a UNS test (typically, with two different UNSs).
Each UNS test includes:

  Retelling
    - play the recording of the story for the UNS a few times
    - ask the UNS to tell the story in his or her own words, but trying not to leave anything out
    - play the recording again and ask UNS to compare what they said with the recording (to correct it)
    - ask for another retelling and this time record it (repeat as necessary)

  English/National language back-translation
    - with a 2nd recording devicing recording, play short portions of the original story (i.e. phrase-
      by-phrase or line-by-line) and ask the UNS to give the translation of each portion into English
      or the national language

  Inference testing questions
    - play the portion of the original story recording upto a line in the story that has one or more
      inference testing questions ('tst:' lines). Stop the play back, ask the UNS the question(s), 
      and with another recording device record their response(s).

When you are finished, then click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the 
next (green) state, where you will listen to the three recordings you have made above (i.e. the 
Retelling, the back-translation, and the answers to the testing questions) to enter the UNS's responses 
into the story documentation.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacEnterRetellingOfTest1</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacOnlineReview1WithConsultant</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacAddStoryQuestions</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="false" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eProjFacEnterRetellingOfTest1" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator enters retelling back-translation</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the Project Facilitator) will enter the back-translation of the UNS's retelling 
of the story.

When you enter this state, you will be asked if you want to add boxes for the test results. If you 
click 'Yes', then one set of 'retelling' boxes will appear below the story line boxes in which you 
can enter the retelling from the UNS.

It is normally the case that you will do a UNS test with two different UNSs. So ultimately you will 
need two sets of responses to back-translate into English and enter. However, the program will want 
to get all of the responses from the first UNS first (here for his or her 'retelling' and in the 
next state, the answers to the testing questions). This way, all the responses can be associated 
with the same UNS. Once you finish entering the retelling and (in the next state) the answers to the 
testing questions, then you will want to come back to this state again, click 'Yes' to add a 2nd set
of boxes and enter the results from the 2nd UNS.

When you are finished entering the retelling, then click the "Select State" menu item and in the 
resulting window click on the next (green) state, which is for entering the answers to the inference 
testing questions of this same UNS.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacEnterAnswersToStoryQuestionsOfTest1</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReadyForTest1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacOnlineReview1WithConsultant</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestions="false" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eProjFacEnterAnswersToStoryQuestionsOfTest1" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator enters answers to the story questions from the UNS test</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the Project Facilitator) will enter the UNS's responses to the inference testing 
questions.

Entering this state will cause one set of 'answer' boxes to appear underneath the testing questions 
in which you can enter the response from the UNS.

After you are finished, if you want to enter the results (i.e. retelling and answers) for a 2nd UNS 
test, then click the 'Select State' button and click on the previous (red) state button, 'Project 
Facilitator enters retelling back-translation'. You will be asked if you want to add a set of boxes 
for the UNS's responses (you will want to click 'Yes').

Otherwise, if you're finished entering in UNS test results, then click the "Select State" menu item 
and in the resulting window click on the next (green) state.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTypeInternationalBTTest1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck2</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheck2</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacEnterRetellingOfTest1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReadyForTest1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacOnlineReview1WithConsultant</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="false" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eProjFacRevisesAfterUnsTest" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator" DontShowTilPast="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator revises the story (after UNS test)</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the project facilitator) will go through the feedback given by the consultant in the Consultant
Notes pane and revise your story and then send it back to the Consultant and then Coach *before* doing a UNS test. 
Generally, you will be in this state when the consultant/coach wants you to make some change to the story and they 
want to review your changes before having you go on to do a UNS test. So they will have moved the story *backwards* 
from a later state into this earlier state for you to make changes.

As you process the consultant's comments, decide on the appropriate change for each comment and then get the crafter
to make a new recording incorporating all of the changes.

Once you and the crafter have made revisions/corrections and have a new recording, then update the story line text
boxes with the change as well as the optional national language and English back-translations.

For each comment by the consultant (in the 'cons:' field of the 'Consultant Notes' pane) you should type in some
response in the boxes labeled 'prfc:' (for Project Facilitator) to close the loop on the conversation (even just "done"
is fine). If you have further questions, it's okay to ask for clarification in another line. You can add another line
for additional comments by right-clicking on the small button and choosing "Add Note" if one is not already visible.

When you are finished, then click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the next (green)
state.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTypeInternationalBTTest1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck2</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheck2</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eBackTranslatorTypeInternationalBTTest1" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eEnglishBacktranslator" RequiresUsingEnglishBT="true" RequiresUsingOtherEnglishBTer="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>English back-translator enters the English BT of the UNS test results</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, someone typically outside of the crafting team will translate the responses from the
UNS tests (and update the latest version of the story BT) from the National language into English 
(or from the story language if not using the national language back-translation).

This stage only occurs if you have an "Outside English Back-translator" member on your team (see
"Project", "Settings" and the "Team Members" tab). This state occurs after all the Project Facilitator 
states are finished and just before the story goes to the consultant. 

There are not separate boxes for the English back-translation of the test responses, so you can just
add the English BT to the same boxes that have the vernacular or national language responses.

When you are finished entering the English back translation, then click the "Select State" menu item 
and in the resulting window click on the next (green) state.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck2</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheck2</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesAfterUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eFirstPassMentorCheck2" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eFirstPassMentor" RequiresFirstPassMentor="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>First-pass mentor checks UNS test results</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the first-pass mentor) will check the story again now that you have the answers to the story testing questions 
and the retelling testing from the UNS(s). You should make any suggestions you think would help make the story more accurate, 
clear, and natural. You will put your suggestions in the 'Consultant Notes' pane of the editor in the boxes labeled 'cons:'

As before, you can make comments related to any of the following issues:

Anchors: are the lines of the story supported by the anchored verses, or has the story crafter misinterpreted something?

Story Flow: does the story flow nicely?

Story Length: is the length of the story nice? Does it seem re-tellable?

Translation issues: are any words translated in a way that makes you think it might be mis-translated?

Story matches the stated purpose: does the story seem to support the purpose for which it was created? (see 'Story' menu, 'Story 
    Information' to see the 'Purpose'). The redemptive theme is also supposed to be written up in the first tab of the 'Show 
    Panorama' command.

Additionally, during this state you will have UNS responses to the Testing Questions and retellings of the story from the UNS 
test(s). Review the answers that the UNS gave to the story and see if any of the answers suggest that the story is unclear or 
misleading at any point. If so, then be sure to make a comment about it in the consultant notes pane.

Also, look at the retelling and if it is significantly different from the original story and especially if it seems more natural 
to you, then make a suggestion about that to the crafting team as well (i.e. to consider whether the retelling is a more natural 
way to say it and therefore perhaps the original story ought to be changed).

When you are finished reviewing the Story and putting any consultant notes you have in the 'Consultant Notes' pane, then click 
the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the next (green) state.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCheck2</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTypeInternationalBTTest1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesAfterUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eConsultantCheck2" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Consultant checks story after UNS test</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) will check the story again now that you have the answers to the story testing questions and the retelling 
from the UNS(s). You should make any suggestions you think would help make the story more accurate, clear, and natural. You will put your 
suggestions in the 'Consultant Notes' pane of the editor in the boxes labeled 'cons:'

As before, you can make comments related to any of the following issues:

Anchors: are the lines of the story supported by the anchored verses, or has the story crafter misinterpreted something?

Story Flow: does the story flow nicely?

Story Length: is the length of the story nice? Does it seem re-tellable?

Translation issues: are any words translated in a way that makes you think it might be mis-translated?

Story matches the stated purpose: does the story seem to support the purpose for which it was created? (see 'Story' menu, 'Story Information' 
    to see the 'Purpose'). The redemptive theme is also supposed to be written up in the first tab of the 'Show Panorama' command.

Additionally, during this state you will have UNS responses to the Testing Questions and retellings of the story from the UNS test(s). Review 
the answers the UNS gave to the story and see if any of the answers suggest that the story is unclear or misleading at any point. If so, then 
be sure to make a comment about it in the consultant notes pane.

Also, look at the retelling and if it is significantly different from the original story and especially if it seems more natural to you, then 
make a suggestion about that to the crafting team as well (i.e. to consider whether the retelling is a more natural way to say it and therefore 
perhaps the original story ought to be changed.

When you are finished reviewing the Story and putting any consultant notes you have in the 'Consultant Notes' pane, then click the "Select 
State" button to move to the next (green) state.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eCoachReviewRound2Notes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eTeamComplete</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck2</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesAfterUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eConsultantCauseRevisionAfterUnsTest" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining" RequiresBiblicalStory="true" RequiresManageWithCoaching="true" DontShowTilPast="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Consultant revises feedback based on Coach feedback (going backwards after UNS testing)</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) will go through the feedback given by the coach in the Coach Notes
pane and, if necessary, modify or add to your feedback to the project facilitator.

For each comment by the coach (the comments in the "coch:" lines in the Coach Notes pane), you should
give some response to close the loop on the conversation (even just "done" is fine). If you have further
questions, it's okay to ask for clarification in another line.

You can add another line for additional questions/comments by clicking the "Add Note" button if needed.

If you are in this state, it is likely because the Coach was not satisfied with something about the story,
which will require the Project Facilitator and Crafter to correct the story and then return it to the 
coach for review (before doing any further UNS testing). So if you worked with the Project Facilitator
directly making the requested changes, then you can click 'Next State' to return it to the Coach for 
review. Otherwise, if you are just updating the Consultant Notes pane to send it on to the Project 
Facilitator to process the feedback, then when you are finished updating your feedback, click the 
'Select State' button and choose the previous (red) state (e.g. 'Project Facilitator revises the story 
(after UNS test)') for the Project Facilitator/Crafter to correct the story.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eCoachReviewRound2Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck2</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTypeInternationalBTTest1</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesAfterUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="true" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eCoachReviewRound2Notes" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eCoach" RequiresBiblicalStory="true" RequiresManageWithCoaching="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Coach reviews story/CIT feedback (including UNS testing results)</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the coach) will check the UNS test results and the consultant notes added by the
consultant-in-training (and possibly the first-pass mentor) in the Consultant Notes pane.

Any feedback you have can be put into a note in the "Coach Notes" pane. You can click on the "Add 
Note" button to enter the comment you have in the line labeled, "coch:".

If you are satisfied that the story is ready to go on to 'Story Fellowship Group' testing, then click 
the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window click on the next and final (green) state, 
"Story testing complete (waiting for panorama completion review)"

If you are not satisfied with the story and would like further revisions and/or UNS tests, then indicate 
what changes you want in the Coach Notes pane and click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting 
window click on the previous (red) state, "Consultant revises notes based on Coach's feedback". This will 
put the story in the state where the CIT can revise his or her feedback and send it back to the project 
facilitator for changes.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition AllowToSkip="true">eConsultantFinalCheck</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eTeamComplete</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantCauseRevisionAfterUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantReviseRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="false" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="true" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eConsultantFinalCheck" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining" RequiresBiblicalStory="true" RequiresManageWithCoaching="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Consultant does final work (after coach's final comments)</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant-in-training) will process any final comments by the coach, possibly
sending it back to the project facilitator to implement further changes. Being in this state means the 
coach is satisfied with the story (with possible feedback that might need to be processed).

After processing the coach's feedback, if you are satisfied that the story is ready to go on to 
'Story Fellowship Group' testing, then click the "Select State" menu item and in the resulting window 
click on the next and final (green) state, "Story testing complete (waiting for panorama completion 
review)"

If you are not satisfied with the story and would like further revisions and/or another UNS test, then 
indicate what changes you want in the Consultant Notes pane and click the "Select State" menu item and 
in the resulting window click on the previous (red) state, "Project Facilitator revises story based on 
Consultant's feedback". This will put the story in the state where the PF can do further changes.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableForewardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eTeamComplete</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableForewardsTransitions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck2</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesAfterUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eCoachReviewRound2Notes</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="false" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="true" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
  <StateTransition stage="eTeamComplete" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator" RequiresBiblicalStory="true">
    <StageDisplayString>Story testing complete (waiting for panorama completion review)</StageDisplayString>
    <StageInstructions>
In this stage the story has preliminary approval to be used in a Story Fellowship Group (SFG) for its final testing 
(i.e. whether any revisions were necessary based on how it worked in the SFG).

If you have any changes as a result of the SFG, then you can make your edits to the story and return it to one of 
the previous states for either the first-pass mentor or consultant to review. 

To return to one of these previous states, click on the "Select State" menu item and choose the state you want to 
return to shown in red.
    </StageInstructions>
    <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
      <AllowableTransition>eCoachReviewRound2Notes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eConsultantReviseRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eFirstPassMentorCheck2</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes</AllowableTransition>
      <AllowableTransition>eProjFacRevisesAfterUnsTest</AllowableTransition>
    </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
    <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestions="true" viewStoryTestingAnswers="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="true" viewNetBible="true" />
  </StateTransition>
</ProjectStates>