<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ProjectStates>
    <StateTransition StageName="eProjFacTypeVernacular" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator enters the story in the language of the stories</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
By this stage, you will have already crafted and recorded a story according to the procedure you learned in the workshop. See the document "Steps in the Story Crafting Process.doc" for details.

Now you should listen line-by-line to the recording and type it in the verse field in this window.

You can type the entire story into a single verse box. Then when you're finished, click on the "Next State" button in the lower left corner of the screen and the program will ask if you want the story to be split into sentences so that each verse line has a single sentence in it. You can also use the 'Story' menu, 'Split into Lines' command, which will be visible if the entire story is in a single verse box.

The lines will be split into sentences based on Sentence Final punctuation (i.e. ".!?", etc). If your language has special sentence final punctuation (e.g. the Hindi Danda '।' or the Arabic '؟'), you will want to add these to the list of sentence final punctuation in the 'Project' menu, 'Settings' command, on the 'Project/Language Settings' tab. When entering special punctuation, be sure to enter the plain (most common) 'full stop' punctuation character as the first one and no spaces between the characters. This (first) character will be used for any sentences that don't have a full stop (i.e. if you forget one, then it will be added to the sentence).

If this is a story from the Bible, then you will also be asked to type in the purpose that this story is in the set; that is, why have you chosen this particular story? How does it fit with the theme of your panorama? You will also enter the list of resources used in crafting the story (audio recordings of Bibles, videos, etc).
		    </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="false" viewEnglishBTField="false" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresUsingVernacular="true" />
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacTypeNationalBT" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator enters a UNS's back-translation of the story into the National language</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you need to find an uninitiated native speaker (UNS) to listen to the story and have him or her "back-translate" the story into the national language (e.g. Hindi). Then you will type the back-translation line-by-line into the verse field(s) in this window.

Be sure to type the UNS's back-translation into the same line number as the story verse to the left, so that the back-translation matches what's in the story verse.

You can toggle between the 'Story' menu, 'Collapse into 1 lines' command (to put all lines into a single box) and the 'Split into lines' command (to split the story into 1 sentence length lines). This will insure that you have the proper punctuation in both the story lines and in the National language back-translation lines.

When you are finished entering the national language back-translation, then click the button in the left-hand side of the status bar with the label 'Next State' to go to the next stage.

You will be asked to identify which UNS did the back-translation. You can also access this and other story information by clicking, "Story", and then "Story Information" command.

If you have a team member with the role "English back-translator", then the next state will be for you, the Project Facilitator, to enter the biblical references, "anchors" for the story. Otherwise, the next state is for you to enter the English back-translation.
		    </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="false" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresUsingNationalBT="true" />
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacTypeInternationalBT" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator enters the English back-translation</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, one of the crafting team will translate the National language back translation of the story into English.

Unlike the last stage, where the National Language back-translation had to done by a UNS, in this state, anyone can do the English back translation. If no one on the crafting team understands English well enough to do an English back-translation, you may be able to arrange with your consultant to have someone else who knows both the national language and English do the English back-translation for you. To do this, you must add that person to your team with the "English back-translator" role.

If you have a separate "English back-translator" member, then instead of this state, the program will go to the stage where the English back-translation is entered after you have entered the anchors and testing questions (because the testing questions will need to be translated into English as well).

But first, discuss with your consultant whether an English back-translation is even needed and whether it can be done by someone else. As long as the first back-translation is done by a UNS, then it's okay to add an 'English back-translator' team member to do the English back-translation. Click, 'Project', 'Settings', and click the 'Add New Member' button to add an "English back-translator" team member.

There's a program called 'Adapt It' that can be used to help make the English back-translation more efficiently. Click on the 'Story' menu, 'Do English Glossing in Adapt It' menu, and then click the "From (National language)" command. This will write the national language back-translation of the story into an Adapt It file so you can use that program to do the English back-translation.

[note: there's another command on the 'Do English Glossing in Adapt It' menu: "From (Story) language (for Discourse Charting)". This command is useful if you want to create the English back-translation directly from your story language (e.g. Kangri) rather than the national language (e.g. Hindi). You might do this primarily if you want to create a discourse chart in the story language itself and have English glosses. However, this cannot be used to populate the English back-translation fields in this program. This is because the English back-translation is supposed to be based on the Hindi back-translation rather than the original story language. Discuss this with your advisor/consultant to know which one you should use.

When you are finished entering the English back translation, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
		    </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresUsingEnglishBT="true" RequiresUsingOtherEnglishBTer="false"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacAddAnchors" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator adds biblical anchors</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, one of the crafting team will go through the story verse-by-verse and look up one or more Bible references in the Bible pane that supports the information in the verse. These Bible references are known as "Anchors", because they tie the story verse to the Bible.

For example, if your story verse were, "First of all, God made heaven and earth", then you could use the reference "Gen 1:1" as the anchor, which in the NetBible says, "In the beginning God created the heavens and the earth". You could also include another anchor like "Col 1:16", which says, "for all things in heaven and on earth were created by him..." Both of these passages support the idea that "First of all, God made heaven and earth".

When you find a supporting Bible passage, then click and hold down the left mouse button on the button to the left of the Bible passage in the Bible pane. Then while the left mouse button is held down, drag the mouse onto the line in the story verse area above with the label, "anc:". This is the anchor bar for the verse. When the mouse is over the anchor bar, release the left mouse button and a new "anchor button" will appear on the anchor bar for that passage.

Now, you can click on the anchor button to jump to the anchored verse. You can also right-click on the anchor button for other options, like adding a comment to the anchor (e.g. "implied by ..."). These comments will be displayed when you hover the mouse over an anchor button. You can also add a cultural or exegetical note about the anchor by right-clicking on the anchor button and choosing "Add Exegetical/Cultural Note". Such notes can help the consultant understand why you chose the Bible reference that you did.

In the Bible pane in the lower left, by default the NetBible version of the Bible will be displayed. In the upper portion of that pane, there are several small "radio buttons" with labels like "NETfree" (which refers to the NetBible) and "Other". Click on the "Other" button to view different Bible text resources that may be installed on your computer, such as a Hindi Bible translation or an Easy English version of the Bible. Talk with your workshop advisor for other options available.

Remember that each verse must have at least one anchor. 

In this stage, you can also select the key terms that are in the story line. To do this, right-click on the Anchor bar and choose "Edit Key Terms". This will bring up the Key Terms dialog box which will show you all the Key biblical terms associated with your anchored verses. It will also list all the story verses in your project which use the same key term as those in the anchored scripture passages. This is so that you can make sure that you are using the same term in each place where the same underlying Greek or Hebrew word is used.

To work on the key terms, you first select one of the key terms shown in the table at the top of the Key Terms dialog box (for example, "אֱלֹהִים", which means 'god; gods; God'). Then in the lower portion of the Key Terms dialog box will be listed all the story verses where the same key term is used (based on the anchors of all the story verses in the project). 

To indicate which word in the (lower portion) story line corresponds to the key term (in the upper portion), double-click on the word in the lower portion of the screen to select it. Once the proper term is selected in the story language column, then press the "+" key to add the selected word to the list of "Renderings" shown in the fourth column of the table.

You can also edit the renderings by double-clicking on the row in the table, which brings up the Edit Renderings dialog box. All renderings of the same key term must be separated by a comma and a space. In this dialog box, you can also enter notes about the key term (why you chose it, whether it has any special cultural significance, etc).

All of the verses in all of your stories that have the same key term will be displayed in the lower portion of the screen. You'll want to go through all the lines one by one and either make sure the rendering of the key term is in bold (which means it matches one of the already existing renderings) or if the word for the key term doesn't exist, then click the box with the red 'X' in it. This says that that the key term doesn't show up in this verse of the story. This might happen, for example, if instead of using the proper name for 'God' in some particular story verse, you use a pronoun instead. The pronoun shouldn't be listed as a rendering of the key term, so you can click the red 'X' to 'deny' that it's necessary for this particular verse. It might also happen that an anchor is used for only one portion of the underlying scripture passage, so while in a scripture translation, the key term may be necessary, it's possible that in a story, some portion of that scripture verse may be left out. 

When all the stories have either a check mark (indicating that the rendering of the key term is in that verse) or have been 'denied', then you can click the 'X' in the upper right corner of the Key Terms dialog box to dismiss it. You will be asked if you want to save the changes and you should say "yes".

When you are finished adding one or more anchors for each verse, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
		    </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="false" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacAddStoryQuestions" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator adds story testing questions</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, one of the crafting team will go through the story and add "Story Testing Questions" (STQs). These are questions that you will eventually ask an uninitiated native speaker (UNS) in order to test the implications of the story.

The best kind of STQs are those that invite the UNS to speculate on "Why" or "How" of what is going on in the story. Or questions that ask, "What kinds of things might be an example of this?" are also useful. They should be based on the story, but you should try to get the UNS to speculate beyond what the story itself says. For example, suppose that the story had a verse like, "And the people took baptism and left their sins". You could ask a question like, "Why (or how) do you think they took baptism?" or "How (or why) do you think they left their sins?" These would be good questions, because the answer isn't in the story and based on what the UNS thinks, it might be necessary to revise the story to avoid a wrong understanding. 

Other kinds of questions that begin with "What", "Who", "When", "Where", are usually not as good, especially if they can be answered from the story itself. For example, suppose the story verse says, "Jesus and three of his disciples went up on a hill..." Then the question, "How many disciples went up on the hill with Jesus?" would not be a good question, because the answer was just mentioned in the story. Such questions are known as "closed questions" and are not good questions to test the story.

Also, story testing questions shouldn’t be questions for which the answer is either "yes" or "no". For example, a question like, "Did Joseph reveal himself to his brothers before they left?" Also, questions about what something means are not good questions. For example, "What does the phrase "sabt din" mean?". These are examples of questions that are not good story testing questions.

Also, they also shouldn’t be questions which ask the UNS for their personal beliefs or theological opinion (e.g. "Do you think that God could really have created the world in 6 days?") or questions which can't really help the story regardless of the answer (e.g. "In your opinion can a person stay in a cattle shed?"). Besides being a "yes-no" question, this one can't possibly help correct any misinterpretation from the story, regardless of what answer is given.

When you think of questions to ask, keep in mind what kind of answer you might get from the UNS. If the answer could show that they misunderstood the situation in the story, then it's probably a good question.

Depending on what agreement you make with your consultant and coach, you may need to translate the testing questions you create into English so the consultant and coach can review them. However, remember that these questions should always be asked and answered with the UNS in the story language itself; not the national language, nor in English. And they should use the exact same wording as in the story itself. So, for example, if the story said, "Adam was given the fruit and he ate.", then don't word the question as, "Why do you think Eve gave the fruit to Adam to eat?" (since the story verse didn't mention Eve, you shouldn't add her to the question.

You should have at least half as many story testing questions as verses in the story. So if your story is 20 verses long, then you need to have at least 10 questions, and don't forget that it's okay if some verses have multiple questions. If you have trouble coming up with enough questions, then contact your consultant for some suggestions.

When you are finished adding these testing questions, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
	      </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="false" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eBackTranslatorTypeInternationalBT" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eEnglishBacktranslator">
        <StageDisplayString>Special back-translator enters the English back-translation</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, someone typically outside of the crafting team will translate the National language back translation of the story into English (or from the story language if not using the national language back-translation). This is useful for when the crafting team doesn't know English well and someone else can do the back-translation from the national language (which was done by a UNS) into English. 

This stage only occurs if you have an "English Back-translator" member on your team and it occurs after all the Project Facilitator states are finished and just before the story goes to the consultant. During this stage, you, the special English back-translator will translate the story from the National back-translation as well as the story testing questions into English.

There's a program called 'Adapt It' that can be used to help make the English back-translation more efficiently. Click on the 'Story' menu, 'Do English Glossing in Adapt It' menu, and then click the "From (National language)" command. This will write the national language back-translation of the story into an Adapt It file so you can use that program to do the translation.

[note: there's another command on the 'Do English Glossing in Adapt It' menu: "From (Story) language (for Discourse Charting)". This command is useful if you want to create the English back-translation directly from your story language (e.g. Kangri) rather than the national language (e.g. Hindi). You might do this primarily if you want to create a discourse chart in the story language itself and have English glosses. However, this cannot be used to populate the English back-translation fields in this program. This is because the English back-translation is supposed to be based on the Hindi back-translation rather than the original story language. Discuss this with your advisor/consultant to know which one you should use.

When you are finished entering the English back translation, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
		    </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresUsingEnglishBT="true" RequiresUsingOtherEnglishBTer="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eConsultantCheckNonBiblicalStory" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining">
        <StageDisplayString>Consultant checks the discourse features of the story</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) will help the team chart this story in the "Discourse Chart Helper" program.

To copy the story from this program to use in the Discourse Chart Helper program, you can click 'Edit', 'Copy', 'Story' command and then paste the copied text into the 'Workspace' area at the bottom of that Discourse Chart Helper program.

If the team (or you) have used Adapt It to gloss the story into English (see 'Story', 'Do English Glossing in Adapt It' menu and the "From (Story) language (for Discourse Charting)" command, then you can use the "Lookup" converter for the Adapt It '(Story language) to (English) adaptations' project as your glossing SILConverter in the Discourse Chart Helper.

See the instructions in the 'Start', 'All Programs', 'SIL Converters', 'Help', 'Readme for Discourse Chart Helper' program for details.

This is the final stage of the process for this non-biblical story.
		    </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
        <StageRequirements RequiresBiblicalStory="false"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eFirstPassMentorCheck1" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eFirstPassMentor">
        <StageDisplayString>First-pass mentor checks the story</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the first-pass mentor) will check the story and make any suggestions you can think of that would make the story more accurate, clear, and natural. You will put your suggestions in the 'Consultant Notes' pane of the editor in the boxes labeled 'cons:'

You can make comments related to any of the following issues:

    Anchors: are the lines of the story supported by the anchored verses, or has the story crafter mis-interpreted something?

    Story Flow: does the story flow nicely?

    Story Length: is the length of the story nice? Does it seem re-tellable?

    Translation issues: are any words translated in a way that makes you think it might be mis-translated?

    Story matches the stated purpose: does the story seem to support the purpose for which it was created? (see 'Story' menu, 'Story Information' to see the 'Purpose'). The redemptive theme is also supposed to be written up in the first tab of the 'Show Panorama' command.
    
    Were enough resources used: look in 'Story' menu, 'Story Information' again to see the list of resources used in crafting the story. Where possible, there should be at least two Bible versions and two visual resources (video and pictures) used when crafting a story.

    Story Testing Questions: are the story testing questions appropriate for the kind of testing that we want in a Storying project? e.g. do they cause the UNS to think outside of the text--"why" and "how" questions are better than "what", "who", "where", "when" kind of questions)? Have the they avoided questions whose answers are "yes" and "no" or questions which ask what something means? Is there a answer to the question which would be beneficial for checking the inferences of the story?

If there are major problems with the flow and/or thematic focus (e.g. it's too long, or doesn't really support the purpose mentioned), you can add a few consultant notes in the Consultant Notes pane and send it back to the Project Facilitator for revision (i.e. before spending a lot of time checking it further and/or passing it along to the Consultant). To send it back to the Project Facilitator for such revisions, click on the small downward arrow to the right-hand side of the 'Next State' button in the lower left corner of the screen. This will bring up a pop-up list of the previous stages. Just select the previous stage to go back to. Then close the editor and the file will be uploaded to the internet where it can be downloaded by the crafting team for revisions.

Otherwise, when you are finished reviewing the Story and putting any consultant notes you have in the 'Consultant Notes' pane, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
		    </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements RequiresBiblicalStory="true" RequiresFirstPassMentor="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eConsultantCheckStoryInfo" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining">
        <StageDisplayString>Consultant checks the story information</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) will check to make sure that the Project Facilitator has entered the following information properly (click the 'Story' menu, 'Story Information' command):

    the crafter's name
    the purpose for this story (does it fit within their redeptive theme--See 'Show Panorama' command)
    the resources used (are the multiple and oral?)
    the name and details about the UNS that did the back-translation
    
You can also take a first pass read through the story to make sure that it flows nicely and fits within the purpose for which it was created. 

If there are major problems with the flow and/or thematic focus (e.g. it's too long, or doesn't really support the purpose mentioned), you can add a few consultant notes in the 'cons:' fields in the 'Consultant Notes' pane and send it back to the Project Facilitator for revision (i.e. before spending a lot of time checking it further). To send it back to the Project Facilitator for such revisions, click on the small downward arrow to the right-hand side of the 'Next State' button in the lower left corner of the screen. This will bring up a pop-up list of the previous stages. Just select the previous stage to go back to and then upload the file (happens automatically when you exit the editor).

Otherwise, when you are finished reviewing the Story Information, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
		</StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
        <StageRequirements RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eConsultantCheckAnchors" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining">
        <StageDisplayString>Consultant checks the story anchors</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) need to check the anchors added by the crafter(s) for each verse of the story.

The anchors shown in the Story pane are actually buttons, which if you click, will jump to the passage in the Bible pane. You need to make sure that all the information in each story line is covered by the anchored verse(s). If the story verse has information which is not in the anchored passages, it's okay for you to add further anchors if you can think of a scripture passage which supports what the story crafter is trying say (or add a consultant note for the crafter to look up the passage and add the anchor themselves).

As you evaluate whether the story verse is a valid interpretation of the anchored verses, in addition to the text in the Bible pane, it is recommended that you look in Translator's Workplace exegetical resources. If you find a passage in a good exegetical resource that supports the rendering of the story crafter (when, perhaps, the scripture passage in the Bible pane doesn't seem to support it), then you can copy the reference from TW and paste it into an exegetical comment line (right-click on an anchor button in the Story pane and choose "Add cultural/exegetical note" and paste the comment from TW).

As you look up passages in the Bible pane, you can right-click on the book name combo box to move to other books in the Bible or click the up/down arrows to shift to the next/previous verse, chapter or book.

When you are finished checking all the anchors, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
		    </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="false" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eConsultantCheckStoryQuestions" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining">
        <StageDisplayString>Consultant checks the story testing questions</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) need to check the story testing questions added by the project facilitator.

As you consider the story testing questions (STQs), keep in mind that their function is to test the implications of the story. The best kind of STQ are those that invite the UNS to speculate on "Why" or "How" of what is going on in the story. Or questions that ask, "What kinds of things might be an example of this?" are also useful. They should be based on the story, but you should try to get the UNS to speculate beyond what the story itself says. For example, suppose that the story had a verse like, "And the people took baptism and left their sins". A good question would be, "Why (or how) do you think they took baptism?" or "How (or why) do you think they left their sins?" These would be good questions, because the answer isn't in the story and based on what answer the UNS gives, it might indicate that the story is giving a wrong understanding.

Less useful are content-questions that begin with "What", "Who", "When", "Where", which can usually be answered from the story itself (e.g. if the story line was, "Jesus and three of his disciples went up on a hill..." Then it wouldn't be as useful to ask questions like, "How many disciples went up on the hill with Jesus?" or "Where did Jesus go?" Such questions are known as "closed questions", because the answer is in the story itself, and they do not make good questions for testing the story.

Also, story testing questions shouldn’t be "yes-no" questions (questions for which the answer is either "yes" or "no"). For example, a question like, "Did Joseph reveal himself to his brothers before they left?" Also, questions about what something means are not good questions. For example, "What does the phrase "sabt din" mean?". These are examples of questions that are not good story testing questions.

Also, they also shouldn’t be questions which ask the UNS for their personal beliefs or theological opinion (e.g. "Do you think that God could really have created the world in 6 days?"). While they might have an interesting answer to such a question and it may help you learn about their culture better, any answer they give to such a question won't help test the implications of the story.

Finally, as you evaluate a question always be thinking about what kind of answer a UNS might give. If the answer can't really help the story regardless of what the answer is, then it is not a good question. For example, a question like, "In your opinion can a person stay in a cattle shed?". Besides being a "yes-no" question, this one can't possibly help correct any misinterpretation from the story, regardless of what answer the UNS gives.

If you feel that any particular question is not a good question, then add a note to the Consultant Note pane for that line recommending that the Crafting team make a change to the question. It is important to indicate why the question is not a good one so that they can learn what our goal is in asking the questions. And also, be sure to offer an alternative suggestion.

When you are finished adding these testing questions, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process. In the next state, the Coach will evaluate your feedback and possibly put comments in the Coach Notes pane, which you will respond to before your feedback goes back to the Crafting team. If you have a question about your feedback prior to passing your comments on to the coach, you can add a question to the Coach Notes pane ("View" menu, "Coach notes field" command) by right-clicking on the small button to the right-hand side of the appropriate line number and choose "Add Note".
	      </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacReviseAndSendBack" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator revises story based on Consultant's feedback</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the project facilitator) will go through the feedback given by the consultant in the Consultant Notes pane and revise your story accordingly. 

As you process the consultant's comments, decide on the appropriate change for each comment and if it's a small change, you can simply record just that changed part and splice the new recording over the old one in the original story recording. It's okay that this will create an odd sounding recording with portions from different recording sessions. 

For example, suppose that the back-translation of your story says that some character in the Bible story said something which they didn't really say--something which is not anchorable. And the consultant points out that the person really said something else instead. Then you would make a recording of the something else (revised) version and overwrite the quote from the original recording.

If you make your revisions/corrections in this manner (i.e. splicing the revisions in the old recording), then you can also update the story line text boxes with the change as well as the national language and English back-translations. But remember, the *change* is to the story *recording*; not the back-translations. The documentation of the story and its back-translations are just reflections of the change to the story recording which is the ultimate product.

For each comment by the consultant (in the 'cons:' field of the 'Consultant Notes' pane), you should type in some response in the boxes labeled 'prfc:' (for Project Facilitator) to close the loop on the conversation (even just "done" is fine). If you have further questions, it's okay to ask for clarification in another line. You can add another line for additional comments by right-clicking on the small button and choosing "Add Note" if one is not already visible.

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
	      </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eConsultantCheckUntilSatisified1" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining">
        <StageDisplayString>Consultant checks the project facilitator's responses</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) can check the responses of the project facilitator.

If you're happy with the responses and feel that the current form of the story is ready for UNS testing, then click 'Next State'. If you have other remaining issues with the story or the project facilitator's responses, then write them up and click on the down arrow of the 'Next State' button and choose 'Project Facilitator revises story based on Consultant's feedback' to give it back to the project facilitator for further processing.
	      </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eCoachReviewRound1Notes" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eCoach">
        <StageDisplayString>Coach reviews round 1 consultant notes</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the coach) will check the consultant notes added by the consultant-in-training (and possibly the first-pass mentor) in the Consultant Notes pane. Any feedback you have can be put into a note in the "Coach Notes" pane. You can right-click on the small button to the right-hand side of the appropriate line number and choose "Add Note" to enter the comment you have in the line labeled, "coch:"

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="false" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="true" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eConsultantReviseRound1Notes" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining">
        <StageDisplayString>Consultant revises round 1 notes based on Coach's feedback</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) will go through the feedback given by the coach in the Coach Notes pane and, if necessary, modify or add to your feedback to the crafting team.

For each comment by the coach (the comments in the "coch:" lines in the Coach Notes pane), you should give some response to close the loop on the conversation (even just "done" is fine). If you have further questions, it's okay to ask for clarification in another line.

You can add another line for additional comments by right-clicking on the small button and choosing "Add Note" if one is not already visible.

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="true" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotes" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>English back-translator translates Consultant Notes for Project Facilitator/Team</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the English back-translator) will go through the feedback given by the consultant in the Consultant Notes pane and translate it into the national language for the project facilitator/crafting team. 

You can just type the translation into the same box as the original consultant note, though you'll have to manually turn on the proper keyboard as needed.

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator revises story based on Consultant's feedback</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the project facilitator) will go through the feedback given by the consultant in the Consultant Notes pane and revise your story accordingly. 

[Before making any changes, however, it is recommended that you keep a copy of the older version of the story so that that consultant or others can see what changes were made. To make a copy, click the 'Panorama' menu, 'Show' command to launch the Panorama View window. Then select the story you want to make a copy of and click the 3rd button own on the right-hand side whose tooltip says, "Copy the selected story to the "Old Stories" list..." This will make a copy of the story in the "Old Stories" list and you can refer to the older version of the story by using the 'View' menu, 'Old Stories' drop down list.]

As you process the consultant's comments, decide on the appropriate change for each comment and if it's a small change, you can simply record just that changed part and splice the new recording over the old one in the original story recording. It's okay that this will create an odd sounding recording with portions from different recording sessions. 

For example, suppose that the back-translation of your story says that some character in the Bible story said something which they didn't really say--something which is not anchorable. And the consultant points out that the person really said something else instead. Then you would make a recording of the something else (revised) version and overwrite the quote from the original recording.

If you make your revisions/corrections in this manner (i.e. splicing the revisions in the old recording), then you can also update the story line text boxes with the change as well as the national language and English back-translations. But remember, the *change* is to the story *recording*; not the back-translations. The documentation of the story and its back-translations are just reflections of the change to the story recording which is the ultimate product.

For each comment by the consultant (in the 'cons:' field of the 'Consultant Notes' pane), you should type in some response in the boxes labeled 'prfc:' (for Project Facilitator) to close the loop on the conversation (even just "done" is fine). If you have further questions, it's okay to ask for clarification in another line. You can add another line for additional comments by right-clicking on the small button and choosing "Add Note" if one is not already visible.

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
	      </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacOnlineReview1WithConsultant" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator has 1st online review with consultant</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the Project Facilitator) will arrange a time to get online at the same time as the consultant so that you can discuss the feedback he or she gave. If your team has a First Pass Mentor, that person should also be involved in this discussion so they can learn as well. Finally, if the team itself is a team that doesn't know English, it might also be necessary to have the person on your team who does the English Back-translation also be present on-line, so that he or she can translate between the team and the consultant.

Once all of the issues and their resolutions are discussed, you can transition to the next state during which you will do your first (formal) UNS test.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacReadyForTest1" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
      <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator is ready for the 1st (formal) UNS test</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the Project Facilitator) will arrange for the first formal test with two different UNSs. As discussed in the process document, each full UNS test includes:

    UNS retelling
    UNS inference testing

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
    </StageInstructions>
        <AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
            <AllowableBackwardsTransition>eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound1Notes</AllowableBackwardsTransition>
            <AllowableBackwardsTransition>eProjFacOnlineReview1WithConsultant</AllowableBackwardsTransition>
        </AllowableBackwardsTransitions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="false" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacEnterAnswersToStoryQuestionsOfTest1" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator enters answers to the story questions from the UNS test</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the Project Facilitator) will enter the UNS's responses to the inference testing questions.

It is normally the case that you will run the test twice with two different UNSs, so you will have two sets of responses to back-translate into English and enter. Entering this state will cause one set of 'answer' boxes to appear underneath the testing questions in which you can enter the response from the first UNS.

You can click the 'Next State' button to go to the next state (where you can enter the retelling responses from the first UNS). If you click the 'Next State' button again--and you've only entered in one UNS's responses, this state will be repeated for you to enter the responses for the second UNS.

Alternately, you can add the other test results even before leaving this state by clicking 'Edit' menu, 'Add test results' command, which will add text boxes for both UNS's answers to the inference testing questions as well as both retelling tests.

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="false" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacEnterRetellingOfTest1" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator enters test 1 retelling back-translation</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the Project Facilitator) will enter the back-translation of the UNS's retelling of the story.

It is normally the case that you will run the test twice with two different UNSs, so you will have two sets of responses to back-translate into English and enter. Entering this state will cause one set of 'retelling' boxes to appear below the story line boxes in which you can enter the retelling from the first UNS.

If you haven't entered the answers to the testing questions and retellings for two different UNSs, then when you click the 'Next State' button, the program will ask you if you want to revert back to the the 'Project Facilitator enters answers to the story questions from the UNS test' state for you to add the test results for another UNS. If your consultant is expecting two UNS tests, then you need to click 'Yes'.

When you are finished entering both retellings, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar and to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="false" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eFirstPassMentorCheck2" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eFirstPassMentor">
        <StageDisplayString>First-pass mentor checks test 1 results</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the first-pass mentor) will check the story again now that you have the answers to the story testing questions and the retelling testing by two different UNSs. You should make any suggestions you think would help make the story more accurate, clear, and natural. You will put your suggestions in the 'Consultant Notes' pane of the editor in the boxes labeled 'cons:'

As before, you can make comments related to any of the following issues:

    Anchors: are the lines of the story supported by the anchored verses, or has the story crafter mis-interpreted something?

    Story Flow: does the story flow nicely?

    Story Length: is the length of the story nice? Does it seem re-tellable?

    Translation issues: are any words translated in a way that makes you think it might be mis-translated?

    Story matches the stated purpose: does the story seem to support the purpose for which it was created? (see 'Story' menu, 'Story Information' to see the 'Purpose'). The redemptive theme is also supposed to be written up in the first tab of the 'Show Panorama' command.

Additionally, during this state you will have UNS responses to the Testing Questions and retellings of the story from the one or two UNS checks. 

Review the answers that the UNS gave to the story and see if any of the answers suggest that the story is unclear or misleading at any point. If so, then be sure to make a comment about it in the consultant notes pane.

Also, look at the retelling and if it is significantly different from the original story and especially if it seems more natural to you, then make a suggestion about that to the crafting team as well (i.e. to consider whether the retelling is a more natural way to say it and therefore perhaps the original story ought to be changed.

When you are finished reviewing the Story and putting any consultant notes you have in the 'Consultant Notes' pane, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true" RequiresFirstPassMentor="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eConsultantCheck2" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining">
        <StageDisplayString>Consultant checks story for round 2</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) will check the story again now that you have the answers to the story testing questions and the retelling testing by two different UNSs. You should make any suggestions you think would help make the story more accurate, clear, and natural. You will put your suggestions in the 'Consultant Notes' pane of the editor in the boxes labeled 'cons:'

As before, you can make comments related to any of the following issues:

    Anchors: are the lines of the story supported by the anchored verses, or has the story crafter mis-interpreted something?

    Story Flow: does the story flow nicely?

    Story Length: is the length of the story nice? Does it seem re-tellable?

    Translation issues: are any words translated in a way that makes you think it might be mis-translated?

    Story matches the stated purpose: does the story seem to support the purpose for which it was created? (see 'Story' menu, 'Story Information' to see the 'Purpose'). The redemptive theme is also supposed to be written up in the first tab of the 'Show Panorama' command.

Additionally, during this state you will have UNS responses to the Testing Questions and retellings of the story from the one or two UNS checks. 

Review the answers that the UNS gave to the story and see if any of the answers suggest that the story is unclear or misleading at any point. If so, then be sure to make a comment about it in the consultant notes pane.

Also, look at the retelling and if it is significantly different from the original story and especially if it seems more natural to you, then make a suggestion about that to the crafting team as well (i.e. to consider whether the retelling is a more natural way to say it and therefore perhaps the original story ought to be changed.

When you are finished reviewing the Story and putting any consultant notes you have in the 'Consultant Notes' pane, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eCoachReviewRound2Notes" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eCoach">
        <StageDisplayString>Coach reviews Round 2 (test 1) feedback</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the coach) will check the consultant notes added by the consultant-in-training (and possibly the first-pass mentor) in the Consultant Notes pane. 

This round will include the responses from the first formal UNS test (by two UNSs).

Any feedback you have can be put into a note in the "Coach Notes" pane. You can right-click on the small button to the right-hand side of the appropriate line number and choose "Add Note" to enter the comment you have in the line labeled, "coch:"

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="false" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="true" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eConsultantReviseRound2Notes" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining">
        <StageDisplayString>Consultant revises round 2 notes based on Coach's feedback</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) will go through the feedback given by the coach in the Coach Notes pane and, if necessary, modify or add to your feedback to the crafting team.

For each comment by the coach (the comments in the "coch:" lines in the Coach Notes pane), you should give some response to close the loop on the conversation (even just "done" is fine). If you have further questions, it's okay to ask for clarification in another line.

You can add another line for additional comments by right-clicking on the small button and choosing "Add Note" if one is not already visible.

You may reach this state again if the coach has any additional feedback after the last round of checking. That is, during the future state of the coach checking the test 2 results, either the coach will approved the story after checking your feedback or not. If he or she doesn't approve the story to move on to the Story Fellowship Group testing stage, then the coach will return the story to this stage for you to provide additional feedback to the team and repeat the this and the next 10 or so states again.

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="true" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eBackTranslatorTranslateConNotes2" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eEnglishBacktranslator">
        <StageDisplayString>English back-translator translates Consultant Notes for Project Facilitator/Team</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the English back-translator) will go through the feedback given by the consultant in the Consultant Notes pane (from round 2; after the 2nd formal UNS test) and translate it into the national language for the project facilitator/crafting team.

You can just type the translation into the same box as the original consultant note, though you'll have to manually turn on the proper keyboard as needed.

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true" RequiresUsingOtherEnglishBTer="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacReviseBasedOnRound2Notes" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator revises story based on round 2 notes</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the project facilitator) will go through the feedback given by the consultant in the Consultant Notes pane and revise your story accordingly. 

As you process the consultant's comments, decide on the appropriate change for each comment and if it's a small change, you can simply record just that changed part and splice the new recording over the old one in the original story recording. It's okay that this will create an odd sounding recording with portions from different recording sessions. 

For example, suppose that the back-translation of your story says that some character in the Bible story said something which they didn't really say--something which is not anchorable. And the consultant points out that the person really said something else instead. Then you would make a recording of the something else (revised) version and overwrite the quote from the original recording.

If you make your revisions/corrections in this manner (i.e. splicing the revisions in the old recording), then you can also update the story line text boxes with the change as well as the national language and English back-translations. But remember, the *change* is to the story *recording*; not the back-translations. The documentation of the story and its back-translations are just reflections of the change to the story recording which is the ultimate product.

For each comment by the consultant (in the 'cons:' field of the 'Consultant Notes' pane), you should type in some response in the boxes labeled 'prfc:' (for Project Facilitator) to close the loop on the conversation (even just "done" is fine). If you have further questions, it's okay to ask for clarification in another line. You can add another line for additional comments by right-clicking on the small button and choosing "Add Note" if one is not already visible.

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacOnlineReview2WithConsultant" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator has 2nd online review with consultant</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the Project Facilitator) will arrange a time to get online at the same time as the consultant so that you can discuss the feedback he or she gave. If your team has a First Pass Mentor, that person should also be involved in this discussion so they can learn as well. Finally, if the team itself is a team that doesn't know English, it might also be necessary to have the person on your team who does the English Back-translation also be present on-line, so that he or she can translate between the team and the consultant.

Once all of the issues and their resolutions are discussed, you can transition to the next state during which you will do your first (formal) UNS test.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacReadyForTest2" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator is ready for the 2nd (formal) UNS test</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the Project Facilitator) will arrange for the second formal test with a third UNSs. As discussed in the process document, the full UNS test includes:

    UNS retelling
    UNS inference testing

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="false" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
        <StageRequirements RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacEnterAnswersToStoryQuestionsOfTest2" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator enters test 2 answers to story testing questions</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the Project Facilitator) will enter the UNS's responses to the inference testing questions from the second formal UNS test.

Entering this state will cause a new set of 'answer' boxes to appear underneath the testing questions in which you can enter the response from the UNS.

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="false" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="false" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eProjFacEnterRetellingOfTest2" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Project Facilitator enters test 2 retelling back-translation</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the Project Facilitator) will enter the back-translation of the UNS's retelling of the story from the second formal UNS test.

Entering this state will cause a new set of 'retelling' boxes to appear below the story line boxes in which you can enter the retelling from the UNS.

When you are finished entering both retellings, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar and to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="false" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="false" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="false" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="false" />
        <StageRequirements RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eFirstPassMentorReviewTest2" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eFirstPassMentor">
        <StageDisplayString>First-pass mentor checks test 2 results</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the first-pass mentor) will check the story again now that you have the answers to the story testing questions and the retelling testing from yet another UNS. You should make any suggestions you think would help make the story more accurate, clear, and natural. You will put your suggestions in the 'Consultant Notes' pane of the editor in the boxes labeled 'cons:'

As before, you can make comments related to any of the following issues:

    Anchors: are the lines of the story supported by the anchored verses, or has the story crafter mis-interpreted something?

    Story Flow: does the story flow nicely?

    Story Length: is the length of the story nice? Does it seem re-tellable?

    Translation issues: are any words translated in a way that makes you think it might be mis-translated?

    Story matches the stated purpose: does the story seem to support the purpose for which it was created? (see 'Story' menu, 'Story Information' to see the 'Purpose'). The redemptive theme is also supposed to be written up in the first tab of the 'Show Panorama' command.

Additionally, during this state you will have responses to the Testing Questions and another retelling of the story from a third UNS (second formal test).

Review the answers that the UNS gave to the story and see if any of the answers suggest that the story is unclear or misleading at any point. If so, then be sure to make a comment about it in the consultant notes pane.

Also, look at the retelling and if it is significantly different from the original story and especially if it seems more natural to you, then make a suggestion about that to the crafting team as well (i.e. to consider whether the retelling is a more natural way to say it and therefore perhaps the original story ought to be changed.

When you are finished reviewing the Story and putting any consultant notes you have in the 'Consultant Notes' pane, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements RequiresBiblicalStory="true" RequiresFirstPassMentor="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eConsultantReviewTest2" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eConsultantInTraining">
        <StageDisplayString>Consultant reviews test 2 results</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the consultant) will check the story again now that you have the another set of answers to the story testing questions and another retelling from a third UNS. You should make any suggestions you think would help make the story more accurate, clear, and natural. You will put your suggestions in the 'Consultant Notes' pane of the editor in the boxes labeled 'cons:'

As before, you can make comments related to any of the following issues:

    Anchors: are the lines of the story supported by the anchored verses, or has the story crafter mis-interpreted something?

    Story Flow: does the story flow nicely?

    Story Length: is the length of the story nice? Does it seem re-tellable?

    Translation issues: are any words translated in a way that makes you think it might be mis-translated?

    Story matches the stated purpose: does the story seem to support the purpose for which it was created? (see 'Story' menu, 'Story Information' to see the 'Purpose'). The redemptive theme is also supposed to be written up in the first tab of the 'Show Panorama' command.

Additionally, during this state you will have responses to the Testing Questions and another retellings of the story from a third UNS (second formal test).

Review the answers that the UNS gave to the story and see if any of the answers suggest that the story is unclear or misleading at any point. If so, then be sure to make a comment about it in the consultant notes pane.

Also, look at the retelling and if it is significantly different from the original story and especially if it seems more natural to you, then make a suggestion about that to the crafting team as well (i.e. to consider whether the retelling is a more natural way to say it and therefore perhaps the original story ought to be changed.

When you are finished reviewing the Story and putting any consultant notes you have in the 'Consultant Notes' pane, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the next stage in the process.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="false" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eCoachReviewTest2Notes" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eCoach">
        <StageDisplayString>Coach reviews test 2 results</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage, you (the coach) will check the consultant notes added by the consultant-in-training (and possibly the first-pass mentor) in the Consultant Notes pane resulting from the 2nd formal UNS test.

Any feedback you have can be put into a note in the "Coach Notes" pane. You can right-click on the small button to the right-hand side of the appropriate line number and choose "Add Note" to enter the comment you have in the line labeled, "coch:"

This is the last formal state of the checking process and so if there are any remaining problems in the story such that it doesn't have formal approval, then rather than going to a 'Next State', you'll want to click on the down arrow on the right-hand side of the 'Next State' button and choose one of the previous states (in this case, the 'Consultant revises round 2 notes based on Coach's feedback') to return to. The consultant will then revise/add your additional feedback and send it back to the project facilitator for revisions and repeat the last 10 stages or so.

If your additional feedback is only for the benefit of the consultant (and will not lead to any revision by the project facilitator/team), then you can (again) click on the down arrow on the right-hand side of the 'Next State' button and choose the 'Consultant reviews test 2 results' state, which just sends it back to the consultant for feedback.

When you are finished, then click the 'Next State' button in the left-hand side of the status bar to go to the final 'Story testing complete (waiting for panorama completion review)' stage.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="false" viewNationalLangField="false" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="true" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
    <StateTransition stage="eTeamComplete" MemberTypeWithEditToken="eProjectFacilitator">
        <StageDisplayString>Story testing complete (waiting for panorama completion review)</StageDisplayString>
        <StageInstructions>
In this stage the story has preliminary approval to be used in a Story Fellowship Group (SFG) for its final testing (i.e. whether any revisions were necessary based on how it worked in the SFG).

If you have any changes as a result of the SFG, then you can make your edits to the story and return it to one of the previous states for either the first-pass mentor or consultant to review. To return to one of these previous states, click on the down arrow on the right-hand side of the 'Next State' button and choose the state you want to return to (either the 'Consultant reviews test 2 results' state, or if your team has a first-pass mentor, to the 'First-pass mentor checks test 2 results' state), which sends it to them for another consultant check.
        </StageInstructions>
        <ViewSettings viewVernacularLangField="true" viewNationalLangField="true" viewEnglishBTField="true" viewAnchorField="true" viewStoryTestingQuestionField="true" viewRetellingField="true" viewConsultantNoteField="true" viewCoachNotesField="true" viewNetBible="true" />
        <StageRequirements HasEndOfStateFunction="true" RequiresBiblicalStory="true"/>
    </StateTransition>
</ProjectStates>