<story name="(15) prophesy about Jesus Messiah यीशु मसीह के बारे में" stage="TeamComplete" guid="aa933245-4568-4525-b254-fffb1599bbca" stageDateTimeStamp="2010-10-07T11:52:51">
  <CraftingInfo NonBiblicalStory="false">
    <StoryCrafter memberID="mem-1647c071-4ba9-49e2-865b-a9d2a1259764" />
    <ProjectFacilitator memberID="mem-0eb0ef72-f8d5-4b2f-a185-a27dd6fcce33" />
    <StoryPurpose>to show that Jesus' birth was predicted many years before it happened and that his birth was very important</StoryPurpose>
    <ResourcesUsed>Hindi oral recording of this story</ResourcesUsed>
    <Tests>
      <Test memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec" />
      <Test memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a" />
    </Tests>
  </CraftingInfo>
  <verses>
    <verse guid="a46545f1-d07c-4cea-b0c3-3bbe02a70f60" first="true" />
    <verse guid="4acaa542-f2ce-4148-bb92-e6827a3115c4">
      <Vernacular>परमेश्‍वरै इस्राएली लोग आपणै खास लोग च़ाणै।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>परमेश्‍वर ने इस्रायली लोगों को अपने खास लोग बनाए।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>God chose the Israelites as his special people.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Gen 12:2">
          <toolTip>Gen 12:2-3</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <TestQuestions>
        <TestQuestion visible="true" guid="27bb2b93-85dd-4d80-bc62-cf0d4ecd57e6">
          <TQVernacular>परमेश्‍वरै इस्रायली कैलै चाणै आपणे खास लोग?</TQVernacular>
          <TQNationalBT>परमेश्‍र ने इस्रायलियों को अपने खास लोग क्‍यों बनाया?</TQNationalBT>
          <TQInternationalBT>Why did God choose the Israelites as his special people?</TQInternationalBT>
          <Answers>
            <answer memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">परमेश्‍वर ने उनको खास लोग इसलिए बनाया ताकी उनके ज़रिए दुनिंया से पाप को मिटा सके। God made them his special people so that through them sin could be removed from the world.</answer>
            <answer memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">ताकी वो लोग दुसरे देशों में जाकर पाप से बचने का सन्‍देश दे। So that those people could go to other countries and give the message of being saved from sin.</answer>
          </Answers>
        </TestQuestion>
      </TestQuestions>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">परमेश्‍वरै इस्राएल ज़ाती रै लोग आपणै खास आदमी चाणै। God chose the people of Israel race as his special people.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">परमेश्‍वरै इस्राएली लोग आपणै खास लोग च़ाणा। God chose the Israelites as his special people.</Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="f871ddf8-2bce-4037-9a3c-6735c07e5e2f">
      <Vernacular>परमेश्‍वर च़ाह थौ कि आपणे लोगु रै ज़रिए पापा कु बच़ाउणै रौ सन्‍देश पुरी दुनिया दी पऊंच़ी सका।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>परमेश्‍वर चाहता था कि अपने लोगों के जरिए पाप से बचाने का सन्‍देश पुरी दुनींया में पहुंच सके।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>God wanted the message of salvation to reach the whole world through his people.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Gen 12:3">
          <toolTip>Gen 12:3</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Gen 22:18">
          <toolTip>Gen 22:18</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Gen 26:4">
          <toolTip>Gen 26:4</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Gal 3:8">
          <toolTip>Gal 3:8</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <TestQuestions>
        <TestQuestion visible="true" guid="cb232b00-4dd2-4aeb-8ac6-92661adf3fc4">
          <TQVernacular>परमेश्‍वर किणौ संदेश च़ाहा थौ पूरी दुनिया दी पहुंच़ाउंणौ? </TQVernacular>
          <TQNationalBT>परमेश्‍वर कैसा संदेश चाहाता था पूरी दुनिया में पहुंचाना?</TQNationalBT>
          <TQInternationalBT>What kind of message did God want to spread throughout the world?</TQInternationalBT>
          <Answers>
            <answer memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">परमेश्‍वर चाहता था की लोगों के मन में जो मरने का डर है उनसे वो बेफिकर हो कर रहे। God wanted that people should be free in their minds from the fear and anxiety of death.</answer>
            <answer memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">पाप से बचने का। Of being saved from sin.</answer>
          </Answers>
        </TestQuestion>
      </TestQuestions>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">परमेश्‍वर च़ाह थौ की आंउ आपणै लोगु रै ज़रिऐ पापा कु बच़ाउणै रौ ज़ो सन्‍देश आ तेस पुरी दुनीया दी फैलावा ऊ। God wanted to spread in the whole world the message of salvation from sin through his own people.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">परमेश्‍वर च़ाह थौ कि आपणे लोगु रै ज़रिए पापा कु बच़ाउणै रौ सन्‍देश पुरी दुनिया दी पऊंच़ी सका। God wanted that through his people the message of being saved from sin could reach the whole world. </Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="a8328e1d-9fd0-4aa6-858a-6c4abe90a437">
      <Vernacular>परमेश्‍वरा रै लोग ज़ेबी दु:ख मुसीबता दी हुआ थै, तेबी परमेश्‍वर अलग-अलग गुरु  भेजी़यौ तिंउकै आपणौ वायदौ याद दिलावा थै।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>परमेश्‍वर के लोग जब दु:ख मुसीबत में होते थे, तब परमेश्‍वर अलग-अलग गुरुओं को भेजकर उनको अपना वाइदा याद दिलाते थे।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>When God's people were in some trouble, then God sent various prophets to remind them of his promise.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="2Kgs 17:13">
          <toolTip>2Kgs 17:13</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Heb 1:1">
          <toolTip>Heb 1:1</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <TestQuestions>
        <TestQuestion visible="true" guid="e638a4ca-be47-4dfb-8b41-d3e2736fbdd1">
          <TQVernacular>परमेश्‍वर आपणै लोगु कै केबी और किणी याद दिलावा थौ आपणौ वाइदौ?</TQVernacular>
          <TQNationalBT>परमेश्‍वर अपने लोगों को कब और कैसे याद दिलाता था अपना वाइदा? </TQNationalBT>
          <TQInternationalBT>When and how did God remind his people of his promise?</TQInternationalBT>
          <Answers>
            <answer memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">जब वो सारे लोग मुसिबत में होते थे या दु:ख बिमारियों से परेशान होते थे तो अपने सेवक को गुरु बनाकर भेज देते थे और उनको अपना वादा याद दिलाते थे, की उनको छ़टकारा देने वाला इस धरती पर आ रहा है। When those people were in trouble or suffering from sickness or pain then he would send his servants as prophets and remind them of his promise that one is coming on this earth to deliver them.</answer>
            <answer memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">तरह-तरह के गुरुओं को भेज कर अपने वायदों को याद दिलाता था। By sending different prophets he gave reminder of his promises.</answer>
          </Answers>
        </TestQuestion>
      </TestQuestions>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">तैबै दुनीया रै लोगु लै ज़ेती भी दु:ख मुसीबत औआ थी, तैबै परमेश्‍वर ठारा रौंगा रै गुरु तिंउ काऐ भेजा थौ और तिंउकै अपणौ वादौ याद दिलावा थौ। Whenever suffering and troubles came to the people in the world, then God sent various prophets to them and reminded them of his promise.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">परमेश्‍वरा रै लोग ज़ेबी दु:ख मुसीबता दी हुआ थै, तेबी परमेश्‍वर अलग-अलग गुरु भेजी़यौ तिंउकै आपणौ वायदौ याद दिलावा सा। When God's people were in suffering or trouble, then God sent various prophets to remind them of his promise.</Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="9e623854-8335-4440-8a21-9d581c76eef8">
      <Vernacular>कि आउं एक छ़ुटकारौ दैणै व़ाल़ौ भेज़ा उ, ताकी सेउ इये दुनिया रै लोगु पापा कु बच़ाइ सौका, ज़ो तेस माथै विश्‍वास कौराई।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>कि में एक छुटकारा देने वाला भेजूँगा, ताकि वह इस दुनिया के लोगों को पाप से बचा सके, जो उस पर विश्‍वास करते है।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>That I will send a deliverer, so that he can save the people of this world from sin, those who believe on him.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Ps 18:2">
          <toolTip>Ps 18:2</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Isa 59:20">
          <toolTip>Isa 59:20 Protector = Deliverer in Romans 11:26</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Rom 11:26">
          <toolTip>Rom 11:26</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Isa 49:6">
          <toolTip>Isa 49:6</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <TestQuestions>
        <TestQuestion visible="true" guid="0a6d9566-7ecf-4cae-a2a8-2d1f1131fe6d">
          <TQVernacular>तुमारै विच़ारा ई इयै भविष्‍यवाणी कासरै बारे दी आ?</TQVernacular>
          <TQNationalBT>आप के विचार में यह भविश्‍यवाणी किस के बारे में हैं? </TQNationalBT>
          <TQInternationalBT>In your opinion who does this prophecy refer to? </TQInternationalBT>
          <Answers>
            <answer memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">मसिहा के बारे में। About the Messiah.</answer>
          </Answers>
        </TestQuestion>
      </TestQuestions>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">कि इणौ भी अदमी आशा सा ज़ुण तुमुरी दु:ख मुसीबता कु छ़ुटकारौ दिलावा सा। That like this a man is coming who will give deliverance from your suffering and troubles.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">कि आउं एक छ़ुटकारौ दैणै व़ाल़ौ भेज़ा उ इंऐ दुनीया दी, ताकी सेउ इये दुनिया रै लोगु पापा कु बच़ाइ सौका, ज़ो तेस माथै विश्‍वास कौराई। That "I will send a deliverer to this world so that the people of this world can be saved from sin, who believe on him."</Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="a3f0ee13-85c4-4bbe-b784-63bbaf4e4ea3">
      <Vernacular>एस बच़ाउणै वाल़ै लै इस्राएली लोग मसीह बोला थै।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>इस बचाने वाले को इस्रायली लोग मसीह कहते थे। </NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>This savior was called Messiah by the Israelites.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Dan 9:25">
          <toolTip>Dan 9:25-26 "an anointed one" = Messiah (see NASB this verse).</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <TestQuestions>
        <TestQuestion visible="true" guid="9d0e9cd2-176c-4933-a745-f1164e91d5ba">
          <TQVernacular>तुमारी सौमज़िए मसीह कुण सा?</TQVernacular>
          <TQNationalBT>तुम्‍हारी समझ में मसीहा कौन है?</TQNationalBT>
          <TQInternationalBT>In your understanding, who is Messiah?</TQInternationalBT>
          <Answers>
            <answer memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">मसिहा वो परमेश्‍वर है जिसने सबके बोझ को अपने उपर लिया और दुनिंया को उनके पापों से छुटकारा दिलाया। Messiah is that God who took everyone's burden on himself and gave deliverance from their sins to the world.</answer>
            <answer memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">इस दुनीया में छुटकारा देने वाला ही मसिहा है। The one who gives deliverance to this world only is the Messiah.</answer>
          </Answers>
        </TestQuestion>
      </TestQuestions>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">और तेस छ़ोहरु रौ नांउ पौड़ा बासीऐ मसिहा। And that boy's name was later kept Messiah.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">एस बच़ाउणै वाल़ै लै इस्राएली लोग मसीह बोला थै। The people of Israel called this deliverer the Messiah.</Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="7d7e49aa-d6ec-4904-a4e5-bbcb473bbd30">
      <Vernacular>परमेश्‍वरै आपणै गुरु ज़रिए भविश्‍यवाणी देई कि सेउ बच़ाउणै वाल़ौ मसीह इस्राएल देशा रै बैतलहम गाँवा दी पैदौ हुआ।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>परमेश्‍वर ने आपने गुरु ज़रिए भविश्‍यवाणी दिया कि वो बचाने वाला इस्रायल देश के बेतलहम गाँव में पैदा होगा।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>God through his prophet foretold that the savior Messiah will be born in the village of Bethlehem in the country of Israel.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Mic 5:2">
          <toolTip>Mic 5:2</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">तुमु लै छ़ुटकारौ दैणै वाल़ौ बेतलहम गाँवा दी जन्‍म निंआ सा। For you a deliverer will be born in the village of Bethlehem.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">परमेश्‍वरै आपणै गुरु ज़रिए भविश्‍यवाणी देई कि सेउ बच़ाउणै वाल़ौ मसीह इस्राएल देशा रै बैतलहम गाँवा दी पैदौ हुआ। God foretold through his prophet that the Messiah who would be the deliverer would be born in the village of Bethlehem in the country of Israel.  </Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="9053b30b-eb71-4a7c-8131-af5d4268f6e1">
      <Vernacular>सेउ बिण ब्‍याई छ़ोटुड़ी कु परमेश्‍वरा री आत्‍मा कौरीऐ पैदौ हुआ।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>वो बीना शादी की लड़की से परमेश्‍वर की आत्‍मा के द्वारा पैदा होगा।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>He will be born of an unmarried young woman by the Holy Spirit of God.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Isa 7:14">
          <toolTip>Isa 7:14</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <TestQuestions>
        <TestQuestion visible="true" guid="4788c190-a65c-45d0-9f55-23d27177c85f">
          <TQVernacular>तुमारी सौमज़िए छ़ुटकारौ दैणै वाल़ौ बिण ब्‍याई छ़ोटुड़ी कु किणै कौरी पैदौ औंदौ  औलौ?</TQVernacular>
          <TQNationalBT>तुम्‍हारी समझ में बिना शादी की लड़की से छुटकारा देने वाला किस तरह पैदा होता होगा? </TQNationalBT>
          <TQInternationalBT>In your understanding, how could the deliverer be born of an unmarried young woman?</TQInternationalBT>
          <Answers>
            <answer memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">परमेश्‍वर ने उस को अपनी आत्‍मा से बनाया था जो की बिन ब्‍याही लड़की से जन्‍म लेगा। God had made him by his Spirit so he would be born of an unmarried young woman.</answer>
            <answer memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">परमेश्‍वर की आत्‍मा से पैदा होगा। He would be born by the Spirit of God.</answer>
          </Answers>
        </TestQuestion>
      </TestQuestions>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">और सेउ क्‍वारी छ़ोटुड़ी कु बिण ब्‍याही छ़ोटुड़ी कु जन्‍म निंआ परमेश्‍वरा री आत्‍मा कौरीऐ। And he will be born by the Holy Spirit of God to an unmarried young woman. </Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">सेउ बिण ब्‍याही छ़ोटुड़ी कु परमेश्‍वरा री आत्‍मा कौरीऐ पैदौ हुआ। He would be born by the Holy Spirit of God to an unmarried young woman.</Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="cdb1f3fc-b094-41a9-87b9-41030475475b" visible="false">
      <Vernacular>कैलैकी सेउ परमेश्‍वरा री तरफा कु, लोगु तिंउरै पापा री सज़ा कु बच़ाउणा लै भेज़ौ औंदौ हुआ।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>क्‍योंकि वो परमेश्‍वर की तरफ से लोगों को उनके पापों की सज़ा से बचाने के लिए भेजा हुआ होगा।</NationalBT>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec"></Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a"></Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="93d56d26-e206-4bfa-846f-75d2c256cbbf">
      <Vernacular>सेउ सारै लोगु रै पापा री सज़ा आपू बुगता सा।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>वह सारे लोगों के पापों की सजा खुद भुगतेगा।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>He will himself bear the punishment for the sins of all the people.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Isa 53:5">
          <toolTip>Isa 53:5-6</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Isa 53:11">
          <toolTip>Isa 53:11-12</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">कैलैकी सेउ बादेउ लोगा रै दु:खा रौ बोझ आपु माथै निंआ। Because he will take the burden of the suffering of many people on himself.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">सेउ सारै लोगु रै पापा री सज़ा आपू बुगता सा। He will himself bear the punishment of people's sins. </Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="2f285651-4657-4a17-ba0c-b0b778a8b90b">
      <Vernacular>लोग तेसदी कोड़ै मारा इ, तेसरौ मज़ाक उड़ावा ई।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>लोग उसको कोड़े मारेंगे और उसकी बेइज़ती करेंगे।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>People will whip him, mock him.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Ps 22:6">
          <toolTip>Ps 22:6</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Ps 22:7">
          <toolTip>Ps 22:7</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Isa 53:3">
          <toolTip>Isa 53:3</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Isa 53:5">
          <toolTip>Isa 53:5</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">इदै झ़ांउ की लोग तेस दी कोड़ै ला ई, और तेअरौ मज़ाक उड़ावा ई, तेसरी निन्‍दा कौरा ई। To the extent that people will whip him, and make fun of him and dishonour him.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">लोग तेसदी कोड़ै मारा इ और तेसरौ मज़ाक उड़ावा ई। People will whip him and make fun of him.</Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="54384720-a97c-4f96-b436-7454a4d8178d">
      <Vernacular>इदरा झ़ाऊं कि तेस लोग पोरु झ़ांगा ई।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>यहाँ तक कि उसको लोग मार डालेंगे।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>To the extent that they will kill him.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Isa 53:8">
          <toolTip>Isa 53:8</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Isa 53:9">
          <toolTip>Isa 53:9</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <TestQuestions>
        <TestQuestion visible="true" guid="42198e80-706e-490e-bc1c-b2f2056be412">
          <TQVernacular>तुमारी सौमज़िए मसीहा कैलै झांगाई, सेउ ता आशा बौच़ाउंदै?</TQVernacular>
          <TQNationalBT>तुम्‍हारी समझ में मसीहा को क्‍यों मारेंगे, वो तो बचाने आएगा?</TQNationalBT>
          <TQInternationalBT>In your understanding, why will the Messiah be killed, even though he actually comes to save everybody?</TQInternationalBT>
          <Answers>
            <answer memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">क्‍योंकी लोगों को विश्‍वास नही था परमेश्‍वर पर इसलिए वो मसिहा को मार देते है, जिनको मसिहा कि बातें अंध विश्‍वास लगती थी। Because people did not believe in God  so they killed Messiah, those who thought Messiah's words were blind beliefs.</answer>
            <answer memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">क्‍योंकि कुछ लोग उनसे नफरत करते होंगे इसलिए वे उन्‍हे मरना चाहते है। Because some people hated him so they wanted to kill him.</answer>
          </Answers>
        </TestQuestion>
      </TestQuestions>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">एती नांई बासिऐ तेस लोग पोरु झ़ांगा ई। Not only that but they will later kill him.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">इदरा झ़ाऊं कि तेस झ़ांगा भी। To the extent that they will kill him.</Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="651e13e9-67af-4038-9937-6585e341c811">
      <Vernacular>पर सेऊ तौऐं ज़ीउंदौ औआ सा।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>पर वो फिर से जी उठेगा।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>But he will rise again to life.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Ps 22:10">
          <toolTip>Ps 22:10</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">पर चिजै दिनै सेउ ज़ीउंदौ औआ सा। But on the third day he will become alive.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">पर सेऊ तौऐं ज़ीउंदौ औआ सा। But he will become alive again.</Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="e955fee0-14b8-4bd1-bc82-fd51e726d5db">
      <Vernacular>सेउ लोगु रै ज़ीवा कु पापा दी मौरनै रै डरा गाड़ीयौ, तिउं अंधकारा कु प्‍याशै दी आणा।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>वह लोगों के दिल से पाप में मरने के डर को निकालकर उनको अंधकार से उजाले में लाएगा।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>Having removed the fear of dying in sin from the hearts of people, he will bring them from darkness into light.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Isa 9:2">
          <toolTip>helps to anchor "fill them with light"</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Ps 107:10">
          <toolTip>"utter darkness" = NASB "shadow of death"</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Ps 107:14">
          <toolTip>"utter darkness" = NASB "shadow of death"</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Isa 25:8">
          <toolTip>Isa 25:8-9</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="1Cor 15:54">
          <toolTip>1Cor 15:54-57 - a quotation from Isaiah 25:8</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Heb 2:15">
          <toolTip>anchors "fear of dying"</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Rom 5:12">
          <toolTip>anchors "dying in sin"</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <TestQuestions>
        <TestQuestion visible="true" guid="c7ad68b2-a448-406a-a88d-fbb27caa3293">
          <TQVernacular>पापा दी मौरने रौ डौर का सा?</TQVernacular>
          <TQNationalBT>पाप में मरने का डर क्‍या है?</TQNationalBT>
          <TQInternationalBT>What is the fear of dying in sin?</TQInternationalBT>
          <Answers>
            <answer memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">पाप में मरने का डर था उनको की परमेश्‍वर को ना मानना, वे दु:ख बिमारी में जकड़े हुए थे बस वोही डर था उनको पापों में मरने का। They had the fear of dying in sin, that not believing God, they were in sickness and suffering, they had the fear of dying in sin.</answer>
            <answer memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">[they forgot to ask this question]</answer>
          </Answers>
        </TestQuestion>
      </TestQuestions>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">मसिहा तिंउ लोगु रै ज़ीवा कु मौरनै रौ डौर ज़ो पाप औआ सा तेस मिटाईयौ एक नौंवौ प्‍याशौ आशा तिंउरै ज़ीवा ई। Messiah will remove the fear of death from their hearts, which is sin, and a new light will come into their hearts.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">सेउ लोगु रै ज़ीवा कु पापा दी मौरनै रै डौर गाड़ीयौ, तिउं अंधकारा कु गाड़ीयौ प्‍याशै दी टाला सा। He will remove the fear of dying in sin from their hearts and take them from darkness into light. </Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="0c97ab77-b3af-4dc4-a1d7-e7f6473edf9f">
      <Vernacular>सेउ मसीह ज़ाती-ज़ाती रै लोगु, तिंउरै पापा री सज़ा कु बच़ावा आ।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>वो मसीहा जाती-जाती के लोगों को उनके पापों की सजा से बचाएगा।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>That Messiah will save people of all races from the punishment of their sins.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Ps 65:5">
          <toolTip>Ps 65:5</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Ps 98:3">
          <toolTip>Ps 98:3</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Isa 52:10">
          <toolTip>Isa 52:10</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Dan 9:25">
          <toolTip>Dan 9:25-26 "an anointed one" = Messiah (see NASB this verse).</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <TestQuestions>
        <TestQuestion visible="true" guid="e8eb470d-841c-4118-a997-20bf770206dd">
          <TQVernacular>मसीह लोगु केज़ै कु बौच़ावा सा? </TQVernacular>
          <TQNationalBT>मसीह लोगों को किससे बचाएगा?</TQNationalBT>
          <TQInternationalBT>What will the Messiah save people from?</TQInternationalBT>
          <Answers>
            <answer memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec"> मसिहा उनको पाप से बचाएगा, ओर पाप से छ़ुटकारा देगा। Messiah will save from their sins, and give deliverance from sin.</answer>
            <answer memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">पाप से। From sin.</answer>
          </Answers>
        </TestQuestion>
      </TestQuestions>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">सै लोग परेशान औआ ई तेस देखीयौ, सेउ मसिहा जा़ती-ज़ाती रै ज़ेती लोग औआ ई तिंउलै सौज़ा कु छ़ुटकारौ दिलावा सा। Those people will be troubled, seeing him the Messiah giving deliverance from their punishment to people of all races.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">सेउ मसीह ज़ाती-ज़ाती रै लोगु, तिंउरै पापा री सज़ा कु बच़ावा आ। The Messiah will save people of different races from the punishment of their sins.</Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="a302d5d8-2ad5-4e14-9f39-180826f50cdb">
      <Vernacular>ज़ो तेस माथै विश्‍वास कौरालौ तिंउ सेउ बच़ावा, और परमेश्‍वरा री आत्‍मा कौरीऐ तिंउ भौरा।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>जो उस पर विश्‍वास करेंगे उनको वह बचाऐंगा, और परमेश्‍वर की आत्‍मा से उनको भरेगा।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>He will save those who believe in him and fill them with God's Spirit.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Joel 2:28">
          <toolTip>Joel 2:28-29</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <TestQuestions>
        <TestQuestion visible="true" guid="299aaf5d-5573-400d-b5e9-4cc016830bdc">
          <TQVernacular>मसीहा केज़े आदमी बौच़ावा सा?</TQVernacular>
          <TQNationalBT>मसीह किस अदमी को बचाएगा?</TQNationalBT>
          <TQInternationalBT>What kind of people will the Messiah save?</TQInternationalBT>
          <Answers>
            <answer memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">मसिहा उन को बचाएगा जो परमेश्‍वर के खास आदमी है पाप से तो सभी को छ़ुटकारा दिलाएगा फिर भी जो परमेश्‍वर पर ज्‍यादा तर विश्‍वास करते है उन लोगों को तो हमेशा ही 
बचाएगा Messiah will save those who are God's special people. He will deliver everyone from sin but those who believe much on God, those people he will save for ever/always. </answer>
            <answer memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">जो उस पर विश्‍वास करते है। Those who believe on him.</answer>
          </Answers>
        </TestQuestion>
      </TestQuestions>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">सारै लोग मसिहा माथै विश्‍वास कौरा ई, तैबै मसिहा तिंउ बच़ावा और परमेश्‍वर री आत्‍मा कौरिऐ तिंउ भौरा सा। All the people will believe on Messiah, then Messiah will save them and fill them by God's Spirit.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">ज़ो तेस माथै विश्‍वास कौरालौ तिंउ सेउ बच़ावा, और परमेश्‍वरा री आत्‍मा कौरीऐ तिंउ भौरा सा। Those who believe on him, them he will save and fill them with the Spirit of God.</Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
    <verse guid="a17aa8dc-ca3a-4792-8034-1a254494b285">
      <Vernacular>और आखरी दी मसीह बादल़ा माथै दुबारौ आशियौ आपणै लोगु सरगा दी निंआ सा आपकाऐ, ज़ो तेस माथै विश्‍वास कौराई।</Vernacular>
      <NationalBT>और अन्‍त में वो मसीहा दुबारा बादलों पर आकर अपने लोगों को स्‍वर्ग में ले जाएगा अपने पास, जो उस पर विश्‍वास करते है।</NationalBT>
      <InternationalBT>And in the end, that Messiah will come back on the clouds and take his own people with him to heaven, those who have believed on him.</InternationalBT>
      <anchors keyTermChecked="false">
        <anchor jumpTarget="Dan 7:13">
          <toolTip>Dan 7:13-14</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Dan 9:25">
          <toolTip>Dan 9:25-26 "an anointed one" = Messiah (see NASB this verse).</toolTip>
        </anchor>
        <anchor jumpTarget="Acts 1:11">
          <toolTip>Acts 1:9-11</toolTip>
        </anchor>
      </anchors>
      <Retellings>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-2ddba1d5-8072-47f9-a889-7a993c14abec">और आखरी दी मसिहा बादला दी दुबारौ आशियौ आपणै लोग आपु आइलै सौरगा दी साथा ई निंआ सा, ज़ो तेस माथै विश्‍वास कौराई। In the end Messiah will come again in the clouds and take with himself to heaven those who believe on him.</Retelling>
        <Retelling memberID="mem-7bde86c0-d1a1-4ca2-a69f-dba652e17c8a">और आखरी दी मसीह बादल़ा माथै दुबारौ आशियौ आपणै लोगु सरगा दी निंआ सा आपकाऐ, ज़ो तेस माथै विश्‍वास कौराई। And in the end Messiah will come again to take his own people to heaven, those who believe in him.</Retelling>
      </Retellings>
    </verse>
  </verses>
</story>